<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practise of Christian workes. Written in Spanish by the R. Father Francis Borgia, sometymes Duke of Gandia, and the third generall of the Society of Iesus. Togeather with a short rule, how to live well. Englished by a father of the same society.  VVhereunto are adioyned certaine pious meditations vpon the beades: translated also out of the Spanish</title>
            <author>Borja, Francisco de, Saint, 1510-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898766</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898766</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2006:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practise of Christian workes. Written in Spanish by the R. Father Francis Borgia, sometymes Duke of Gandia, and the third generall of the Society of Iesus. Togeather with a short rule, how to live well. Englished by a father of the same society.  VVhereunto are adioyned certaine pious meditations vpon the beades: translated also out of the Spanish</title>
                  <author>Borja, Francisco de, Saint, 1510-1572.</author>
                  <author>Everard, Thomas, 1560-1633.</author>
                  <author>Cresswell, Joseph, 1556-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 163 [i.e. 263], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 263 misnumbered 163.</note>
                  <note>"Pious meditations upon the beades" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>"The practise of Christian workes" was translated by T Everard. "Pious meditations upon the beades" was translated by J Creswell.--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Stonyhurst College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditation --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:1"/>
            <p>THE PRACTISE OF Chriſtian Workes.</p>
            <p>Written in Spaniſh by the R. Father FRANCIS BORGIA, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes Duke of Gandia, and the third Generall of the Society OF IESVS.</p>
            <p>Togeather with a ſhort Rule, <hi>How to liue well.</hi> Engliſhed by a Father of the ſame Society.</p>
            <p>VVhereunto are adioyned certaine pious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations vpon the Beades<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſlated alſo out of the Spanish.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>seal of Society of Jesus</figDesc>
               <p>IHS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. M.DC.XX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND AND RELIGIOVS MOTHER, <hi>CLARA MARIANA</hi> ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH POORE CLARES IN GRAVELING.</head>
            <opener>
               <pb facs="tcp:151937:3"/>
               <salute>RIGHT REVEREND AND RELIGIOVS MOTHER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I Should mak choice of any other, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your Selfe, to preſent this Booke of <hi>The Practiſe of Chriſtian VVorkes,</hi> vnto; I should not only not diſcharge my debt of ſingular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto You: but alſo ſeeme to commit an offence euen againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:151937:4"/> Authours owne deſire and intention For ſince in the language, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he firſt wrote it, it was dedicated to his Aunt, the worthy Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſſe of the famous mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of your Order, at <hi>Gandia</hi> in Spaine; it may ſeeme, that now, firſt appearing in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, it should, by a pious conſequence, be due vnto you, that are Abbeſſe of the only English Monaſtery, of
<pb facs="tcp:151937:4"/> that Holy Order at this day remayning in the world.</p>
            <p>And when withall, I conſider, how far my ſelfe am growne indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits I haue receaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelfe, and your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Family; I am out of hope to ſatisfy, for the preſent, the leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and ſo am forced to excuſe my ſelfe, by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this intereſt, vntill I may be better able to
<pb facs="tcp:151937:5"/> diſcharge the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall.</p>
            <p>In this little Booke is contained a methode of Meditation, &amp; much matter of ſingular piety and deuotion, both for practiſe &amp; ſpeculation; ſufficient to inflame not only your already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled Hart: but alſo many others, who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, that the celeſtiall incenſe of Prayer may burne continually on the altar of their ſoule.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:5"/>
            <p>I shall not need to ſay any thing of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, whoſe rare ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are ſo known to the World, as they require none of my prayſes: ſince my pen should but blot the fayre paper of his Worth, if I should goe about to blazon them.</p>
            <p>I haue the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly commended this Treatiſe to your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; hoping that your, &amp; the deuotions
<pb facs="tcp:151937:6"/> of your holy family, wil giue it new force; that now tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, it may produce no leſſe copious fruite, then it hath done in the originall Spanish, and other languages.</p>
            <p>Accept then (Right Reuerend &amp; Religious Mother) this poore mite in teſtimony of my true affection; which, I truſt shall heerafter appeare in a more aboundant manner, when my abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb facs="tcp:151937:6"/> shall find a more fortunate ſubiect, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to expreſſe, and shew my ſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your R. euer humble ſeruant in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>I. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:7"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE of the Authour.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Reuerend, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Abbeſſe of the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of <hi>S. Clare</hi> at <hi>Gandia,</hi> his deare Aunt, and Lady in Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERAS my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire (Right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mother) was in ſome part to giue you ſatisfaction, for the many troubles and afflictions,
<pb facs="tcp:151937:8"/> which by my ſinnes I haue cauſed you; I thought I could not do it better, by any other way, then by good workes. But finding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wholy wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my ſelfe, I began to thinke, how I might come to attaine thereto, by practice, and meditating on the moſt holy works of Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, hoping by his merits, and examples to be at laſt able to do ſome good therein. And therefore in this Treatiſe (which I call <hi>An Exerciſe of Chriſtian workes</hi>) I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſet down ſome things which ſeeme to me, may in part ſerue for the making you that ſatisfaction, whereof I
<pb facs="tcp:151937:8"/> ſpake before. Theſe, moſt reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Mother, I now adreſſe &amp; preſent to you, beſeeching you to aſſiſt me with your prayers therein, ſince of my ſelfe, I am in that kind ſo weake and inſufficient, as I dare not aduenture to make you recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without your owne help.</p>
            <p>And no leſſe indeed doe you owe (if not to me, yet at leaſt) to your Lord and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt Ieſus, who offered himſelfe vp to his Heauenly Father, vpon the Croſſe, for our ſinnes. And ſeeing (as the Holy Prophet ſayth) God rendreth to euery one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes; we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:151937:9"/> imbrace that counſaile of the Apoſtle, when he admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs, <hi>to worke, and do good towards all, whilſt we haue tyme: For the night will come</hi> (ſaith S. Iohn) <hi>when none can worke.</hi> Wherefore, as ſoone as any good worke is conceaued and approued by the iudgment of Reaſon, and ſo admitted and accepted of the Will, as that it be determined to do what may be moſt to the glory of God, or profit of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; it muſt diligently, and without delay be put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and execution. For if we neglect to do good, when we may, and are able; great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage will returne vnto vs
<pb facs="tcp:151937:9"/> thereby: and better had it byn not to haue made any purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe therof at al, then afterward not to fullfill, or neglect the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is a common ſaying, that, <hi>Hell is full of good deſires:</hi> howbeit I hould, that there is not a more ſoueraign antidote or more preſent remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euil, then the dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of good workes. For if a man haue ſinned, they help him greatly towardes the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer, and forſaking of ſinne: if he be to make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he cannot performe it better then by good works: if he haue a deſire of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in doing well, he may
<pb facs="tcp:151937:10"/> not better or more readily ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it, then by good workes. For as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> ſayth, <hi>they that worke in me ſhall not ſinne.</hi> And we are to take example of the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> who ſayth in like manner, <hi>My worke is with God:</hi> and all our workes are to be done in God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to his glory, for ſo they will be ſtable and permanent for euer. And becauſe our works cannot be pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, but by Chriſt; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs offer them vnto him, accompanied with the workes of his only &amp; dearely beloued Sonne Ieſus, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, that by his merits and grace, they may be admitted
<pb facs="tcp:151937:10"/> into the ſight of God. For Chriſt did put on our pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he might cloath vs with his riches; and vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to walke, eate, faſt, ſleep, watch, &amp; to do like workes for our profit, that we might offer them to his Father; and by that oblation reape vnto our ſoules no ſmall vtility. And though euery one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his particuler talent giuen him by God, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit more or leſſe by the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of Chriſtian Workes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this direction of ours: yet haue we thought it not amiſſe to ſet downe in the enſuing Treatiſe ſome few thinges, touching this point, that may
<pb facs="tcp:151937:11"/> at leaſt inſtruct, and giue light to the ruder ſort, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſpirit and deuotion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:11"/>
            <head>THE TABLE of the Contentes.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Preface. <hi>pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The firſt Exerciſe. <hi>pag. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond Exerciſe. <hi>pag. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>III.</hi> Exerciſe. VVherin is deliuered, how a ſoule may confound it ſelfe by conſideration of thoſe thinges, that are vnder earth. <hi>pag. 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>IIII.</hi> Exerciſe: wherin is declared, how we ought to confound our ſelues by the conſideration of thoſe things, that we ſee vpon earth. <hi>pag. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>V.</hi> Exerciſe. VVherein is deliuered, how we may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of Celestiall things. <hi>pag. 90.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:151937:12"/>
            <list>
               <head>A SHORT RVLE How to liue well.</head>
               <item>The <hi>VI.</hi> Exerciſe, Of the things, that man is to know for the ſauing of his ſoule. <hi>Chap. I. pag. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the End of man. <hi>Cap. II. pag. 109.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the meanes to come to our End. <hi>Chap. III. pag. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the manner, how to practiſe the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid meanes. <hi>Cap. IIII. pag. 114.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The former part of this Rule.</head>
               <item>The <hi>VII.</hi> Exerciſe, VVhat we should do in the Morning. <hi>Chap. I. pag. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat we are to do at Night. <hi>Chap. II. pag. 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat it is meete for vs to do in the day tyme. <hi>Chap. III. pag. 120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we may be preſent with deuotion at Maſſe. <hi>Chap. IIII. pag. 123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to pray well, <hi>Chap. V. pag. 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:151937:12"/>
               <item>Remedyes againſt diſtractions. <hi>Chap. VI. pag. 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to heare the word of God with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. <hi>Chap. VII. pag. 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we muſt read Spirituall Books. <hi>Chap. VIII. pag. 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manner of examining our Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience. <hi>Chap. IX. pag. 138.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to make a good Confeſſion <hi>Chap. X. pag. 141.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The cauſes, that ought to induce vs to true repentance for our ſyns. <hi>Chap. XI. pag. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The cauſes, for which it is very good, &amp; moſt expedient to go often to Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Chap. XII. pag. 154.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the neceſſity, and vtility of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Cap. XIII. pag. 157.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to communicate with fruit. <hi>Chap. XIIII. pag. 161.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The cauſes, that ought to induce vs to the frequent receyuing of this Sacrament. <hi>Chap. XV. pag. 166.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:151937:13"/>
               <item>Remedyes for the auoyding of ſyns, and reſiſting of tentations. <hi>Chap. XVI.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manner, how to poſſeſſe our ſelues of ſome ſolid Vertue. <hi>Chap. XVII. pag. 173.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond Part of this Rule.</head>
               <item>The <hi>VIII.</hi> Exerciſe. VVhat we are to do in behalfe of God. <hi>Cap. I. pag. 176.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat we are to do in behalfe of the Saints: and namely of the B. Virgin. <hi>Chap. II. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. pag 178.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we are to cary our ſelues towards our good Angel. <hi>Cap. III. pag. 180.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VVhat our Good Angell doth towards vs. <hi>Chap. IIII. pag. 182.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we ought to carry our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our ſelues <hi>Cap. V. pag. 184.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we muſt carry our ſelues towards our Neighbour. <hi>Cap. VI. pag. 186.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we muſt carry our ſelues towards our Superiors. <hi>Cap. VII. pag. 189.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pious meditations vpon the Bead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>p. 193.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151937:13"/>
                  <head>THE PRACTISE OF CHRISTIAN WORKES.</head>
                  <div type="preface">
                     <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HREE thinges there be, wherein it is good to exerciſe the mind, that the workes therof may deſerue to
<pb facs="tcp:151937:14"/> aſcend to the ſight, &amp; preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Gods Maieſty. And theſe be. Firſt, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſelus in euery thing. Secondly, that we giue God thanks. Thirdly, that we craue and aske ſomething at Gods handes. And though a man may indeed exerciſe theſe three in all thinges: yet I meane to accomodate them to ſuch thinges only, which we haue to do dayly. And by theſe you may eaſily vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, how to doe in other thinges, and therefore to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with your firſt workes in the morning, exerciſe your ſelfe as followeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="exercise">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151937:14"/>
                     <head>THE I. EXERCISE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Confuſion.</hi> 1. VVHEN you put on your clothes, be you confounded, that you cloath your ſelfe, when as Chriſt was ſtripped, and left na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon the Croſſe for your ſake.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Thankesgiuing.</hi> Giue him thankes, for that he hath put on our humanity for vs, whome he knew would be moſt vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſo ſoueraigne a benefit: and for that he hath clad vs with the Garment of grace, which we haue ſo often rent in ſunder.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Petition.</hi> Aske, &amp; craue of him, that when putting on your cloaths, you cloath the naked, this worke of mercy may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto him, and beſeech him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151937:15"/> to grant you the ſame, by the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy of that garment, which Herod commanded to be put v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his backe.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Confuſion.</hi> When you go to Church to heare maſſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for that your ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imperfect, you goe to the Church to prayſe God, whome the Angells, that are perfect, do praiſe continually.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>keſgiuing.</hi> Giue God thankes, that though you haue gone out of his houſe ſo often, carryed away by ſinnes, yet he ſtill calleth you home againe, and ſtandeth knocking at your dore.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Petition.</hi> Aske by that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wherwith the moſt Bleſſed Virgin preſented her Sonne in the Temple, you may deſerue to be preſented to God, and to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151937:15"/> made the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When you pray, conſider the multitude of your ſinnes, &amp; ſay with the Publican: <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thanke God, for that Chriſt hath prayed for you, and hath obtayned, that you may be heard, when you pray.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Craue, that by the prayer, which he made in the deſert for ſinners, he wil vouchſafe to gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you thoſe gifts, which he willed vs to aske in the <hi>Pater Noster,</hi> and you ſhall ſay it ouer once.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When you heare Maſſe, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded, for that you haue prepared your ſelfe negligently vnto it, in preſenting your ſelfe before God in Maſſe, and for that the very continuance and long vſe of this benefit, which ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151937:16"/> haue profited you much towards the great eſteeming thereof (for it is a ſigne of Chriſts moſt high charity) hath made you negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and ſo ingratefull.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thanke him, for that he maketh you an Angell, if you confeſſe him, whome you adore with a liuely fayth, ſith it aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to Angells to be aſſiſtant to God, and to praiſe him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Craue, that by that ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice whereof this is a teſtimony, he may imparte vnto you the merits of his bloud: and by the vertue of this ſacrifice, graunt you that aboundance of teares, wherby to waſh away your ſins, and cauſe you to riſe againe with Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When you ſit at the table be confounded for eating of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151937:16"/> bread, to whome you haue beene ſo falſe, vnfaithfull, and ingrate.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thanke him for this, that though you haue hitherto beene, and ſtill are an enemy to him, yet he hath nouriſhed and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned you.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Craue of him, that by that loue, wherewith he filled great numbers of people with a few loaues in the deſert, he will vouchafe to feed you euery day with the bread of his grace.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In buſines, that concernes our owne profit, or our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, we muſt be confounded, for that God pleaſeth to take v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him our, &amp; our neighbours cauſes, who haue beene an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of hurt to our ſelues, and to our neighbours, eſpecially ſith it is a matter of ſo great moment to haue a care of our neighbours
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151937:17"/> good and profit, in ſo much as Chriſt for that cauſe came into the world, that he might take v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him our, &amp; our neighbours cauſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We muſt thanke him, for that, whereas he needed not ſuch buſines at all, yet the ſame are as pleaſing vnto him, as though he ſtood in need of them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. We muſt craue, that by that charity wherwith he ſayd: <hi>I must be in thoſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>inges, that be my Fathers,</hi> he will grant vs to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer occupied in thoſe thinges, that appertayne to his honour, and glory.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When you ſuppe, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded for your negligences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that day, and therefore eate in ſorrow, and ſay with the Prophet: <hi>My teares were to me bread both day and night.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151937:17"/>2. Thanke him, that for you who were ingratefull for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of dinner, he hath prepared a ſupper.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Craue of him, that by that charity, wherwith he gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his laſt ſupper, he may prepare and diſpoſe vs, that we may humbly receaue him, and be euer vnited vnto him with the band of charity.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When you pray at your going to bed, be confounded for that when as Chriſt did v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his Croſſe powre out prayer with ſo great both loue and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for you, yet you loue him but a little, and ſorrow for him leſſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Thanke him for this, that he dyeth, and that you liue.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And craue of him, that by that heauines which himſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151937:18"/> felt dying, and his mother alſo had ſeeing him to dye, he will pleaſe to grant vs this, that both at our owne death, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his, &amp; that for his death our death may be accepted of his eternall father.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When at your going to bed you put off your cloaths, be confounded, for that you deſire to reſt in bed, and without your cloathes alſo; when as Chriſt did for you both ſleep in his cloaths, and had not where to repoſe and lay downe his head.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Giue him thanks for that by thoſe thinges which he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, he deſpoiled you off your concupiſcence.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Finally craue of him, that by the payne which he felt, when being to be crucifyed, he was ſtripped off his cloathes; he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151937:18"/> may ſtrip vs of our euill habits of mind, and conditions, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of earthly thinges we may imbrace the Croſſe, and dying vpon it, may deſerue that nuptial garment, which the eternal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath prepared for all thoſe that loue him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="exercise">
                     <head>THE II. EXERCISE.</head>
                     <p>AND becauſe it would be long to accommodate the forme and manner of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to all our works, that which hath beene ſayd may ſerue to ſhew vnto vs, how other things may be addreſſed according to the ſame rule. And if any ſhall pleaſe further to exerciſe himſelf in other things, he may vſe this forme and manner following.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When he ſtandeth, let him
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151937:19"/> remember Chriſt ſtanding before Pilate the Iudge.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. When he ſitteth, let him conſider Chriſt ſitting, when the wicked mocking him, ſayd: <hi>Haile King of Iewes,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. When he walketh, let him thinke vpon Chriſt paſſing through <hi>Samaria,</hi> and going vp to the Mount of Caluary.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. When he is weary, let him contemplate Chriſt weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his iourney, and ſitting v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Well.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. When he rideth on horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, let him reflect vpon Chriſt ſitting vpon an Aſſe, and entring into the Citty of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. When he viſiteth the ſicke let him reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber Chriſt viſiting and healing the ſicke.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. When his good workes are found fault with, let him cal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151937:19"/> to his remembrance the Iewes accuſation, and their murmuring againſt Chriſt, for healing on the Sabbaoth day.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. When any one giueth him a ſharpe and churliſh anſwere, let him thinke on that anſwere made vnto Chriſt when it was ſayd: <hi>Doeſt thou anſwere the High Prieſt ſo?</hi> And that blow which the wicked miniſter gaue Chriſt vpon his moſt ſacred face.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. When he is angry, let him cal to remembrance that hunger which our Sauiour endured in the deſert.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. When he is a cold, let him remember Chriſt trembling for cold in the manger.</p>
                     <p n="11">11 When he is a thirſt of Chriſt thirſting vpon the croſſe.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. When he is awaked fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſleep, of Chriſt awaked by his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151937:20"/> Apoſtles, when he was a ſleep in the ſhip.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. When he is in diuers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents abandoned o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> friendes: o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt forſaken of his diſcipls leauing him, and running from him.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. When he departeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> friendes: of our Sauiours going from his Mother to his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. When his good workes are detracted: of the detraction of the Iewes, when they ſayd of our Sauiour: <hi>In the prince of the Diuells he caſteth out Diuells.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="16">16. When he ſuffereth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely, or reproachfull wordes openly: of our Sauiour brought forth before the people by <hi>Pilate,</hi> when he ſayd: <hi>Behold the man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="17">17. When he is falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: of Chriſt falſly accuſed in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151937:20"/> 
                        <hi>Caiphas</hi> his houſe.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. When he ſuffereth iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: of Chriſt moſt vniuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. When ſorrow, paine, or ſicknes troubleth a man: let him remember Chriſt ſcourged at the Pillar, crowned with thornes, and nayled vpon the Croſſe, where there was not any whol or ſound part in him from the ſole of the foot to the crown of his head.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Finally when he is at the point of death: let him think vpon Chriſt dying, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his ſpirit into the hands of his Father.</p>
                     <p>And thus may a man in al thinges offer himſelfe to Chriſt, whome he remembreth either to haue done, or to haue ſuffered the like. And ſo of theſe and the like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151937:21"/> effects he, who ſhall out of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity diligently exerciſe himſelfe in this manner, may profit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe much.</p>
                     <p>And becauſe we haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, for the moſt part, layd downe and propoſed examples only of external things without, we haue thought good to add ſome few alſo of things internall or within, and that eſpecially, for ſpirituall perſons, who are not moleſted with the troubles, and trauailes of body ſo much, as with thoſe of ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Wherfore when he ſeeth that the counſaile, which out of his charity, he giueth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is not accepted of, let him remember, that Chriſt gaue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile to many, and yet they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned it.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. When he ſeeth God euery
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151937:21"/> where offended, and he is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and angry thereat, let him remember, that Chriſt was once much mooued at thoſe, who bought and ſold within the Temple, and thereupon draue them out with a whip.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. When he ſeeth ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall friend of his to giue ouer the way of vertue, let him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what our Sauiour thought, and felt in himſelfe, when he ſaw Iudas to abandone, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the way of truth.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. When he conſidereth, how few Paſtours there be in Gods houſe, who exerciſe their functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; charge as they ought, let him call to memory, what Chriſt thought, when he ſayd: <hi>The harueſt is indeed great, but the workemen few:</hi> and for that cauſe how ſorely he wept.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151937:22"/>5. When he is ſorry, and grieued for his owne defects: let him conſider, that our Lord ſaw them before they were, and was ſorry for them.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. When he ſeeth any fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from the ſtate of perfection: let him call to remembrance, how ſorry our Sauiour was for <hi>S. Peters</hi> fall, who had before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed him to be the Sonne of God, and had ſeene his Tranſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration vpon the Mount.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. When he is troubled and preſſed with tentations: let him call to mind the tentations, that our Sauiour endured in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. When he ſeeth the ſociety and company of the good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the bad: let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how Chriſt was afflicted in mind, when the <hi>Geraſens,</hi> to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151937:22"/> whome, moued out of his chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and goodnes, he came, deſired him to depart from them.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. When he is ſorry at his neighbours ſinnes: let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, how Chriſt comming neare to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> wept vpon it.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. When he ſeeth any to haue an imperfect fayth: let him remember, what Chriſt ſayd to his Diſciples, who for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity could not caſt out a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: <hi>O incredulous generation, how long shall I beare with you?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11. When the bad ſcorne &amp; mocke the good: let him remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, how it was ſayd to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vpon the Croſſe: He hath ſaued others, and can he not ſaue himſelfe?</p>
                     <p n="12">12. When they dye who haue liued ill: let him conſider, how our Lord ſorrowed much,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151937:23"/> ſeeing that few would profit themſelues by the effuſſion of his bloud.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. When he feeleth a want of deuotion in himſelfe, let him reflect vpon our Sauiour, when he ſayd: <hi>My God, my God, why had thou forſaken me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="14">14. When any blaſphemeth the name of God, let him thinke that Chriſt had forſeen it long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and was ſorry for it.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. When he ſeeth himſelfe depriued of the familiarity with God, and hath an earneſt deſire to be moſt conioyned with him, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wiſheth to be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and deliuered from out of the dangers of this life, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, how great charity of Chriſt that was, when he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Father for that very thing, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe wordes: <hi>Father, I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151937:23"/> pray for them, that all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe things (I ſay) are to be thus thought vpon, when any thing happeneth, and that our Sauiour in the like caſe thought and did the like: and to him we muſt alwayes offer and preſent whatſoeuer we either do, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. And heerin euery one ought to vſe much care and diligence, and not to ſuffer ſo notable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of profiting his ſoule offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red heereby, to eſcape him. Els it will be a note, not only of a fowle negligence, but alſo of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ingratitude, if we make ſo light an eſteeme of thoſe thinges that concerne our ſoules good ſo much, and may be eaſily obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore I am to intreat
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151937:24"/> and exhort thee, o Soule, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou be, not to neglect ſo great a good, but to conſider, how eaſy a matter it is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat God exacteth of thee, and how great a thing he deſireth to giue thee. For he asketh of thee but thoſe thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, which thou wert bound to do, though he required them not at thy hands: for thou muſt go, walke, eate, take paines, be ſicke, and dye at laſt. All which and ſuch other thinges, if thou doſt, or ſuffereſt for thyne owne ſake, or for the world, beſides that they will be laborious and painefull, thou ſhalt reape no fruit at all by them. But if thou doeſt, or ſuffreſt them for the loue of Chriſt, both thy payne &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour will be eaſed (for Chriſt doth recreate them, who take paynes for him:) and when all thy</p>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div type="exercise">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151937:24"/>
                     <p>them greater then that of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells: Who I ſay, would it not confound, who hath experience of Gods ſo great patience, and ſeeing his iuſtice executed in ſo rigorous a manner towardes the Diuells, yet ſo mercifully affoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him reſpight and tyme of pennance? And this ought to mooue euery one the more, for that men are wont to vſe that diligence in perſwading others to leaue ſinne, which yet we read not any where was done to <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</hi> Neither do men draw others their like into ſinne by wordes and ſignes alone, as <hi>Lucifer</hi> did, but alſo by importune perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, intreaties, money, by threats by honour, by life, and by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer other wayes they can: in ſo much as the malice of men may ſeeme in this reſpect to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151937:25"/> the malice of <hi>Lucifer.</hi> And this alone ought ſo far to depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and abate our pride, and to put ſo great a confuſion into vs, as by it at leaſt in ſome part, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment might be recompenſed which our ſinnes deſerue in hell.</p>
                     <p>To this is further added, that the wickednes (not to ſay the madnes) of men, proceedeth ſo far ſometymes, as it is wont alſo to prouoke the Diuell to tempt them, and to preſent them as it were weapons to kill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: in ſo much as they may ſeeme to do very ill, who are wont to lay all the fault and blame of their hurt vpon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, whereof themſelues are the cauſe. And if thoſe, who haue drawne others into a miſchiefe, dare ſcarcely for very ſhame ſtand amongſt them before a Iudge of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151937:25"/> this world, of how great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thinke you muſt he needs be full, who conſidereth himſelfe to be preſented togeather with the Diuells before the Tribunall of Chriſt?</p>
                     <p>And if a man would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly bethinke himſelfe of theſe things as he ought, he might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily (yea &amp; ought to) be as much confounded for his own malice while he manifeſtly vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, how ſore puniſhments he hath deſerued for his ſinnes, not only in this life, but in that alſo which ſhall neuer haue an end. So doing, all will ſeeme light to him, that he ſuffereth in this life, if he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare it with that, which he was to ſuffer and endure in hell, if God ſhould deale with him according to his deſerts. And therefore let him with all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151937:26"/> confuſion and ſhame, both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his owne miſery, &amp; craue that mercy which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt vnworthy of.</p>
                     <p>And to the end none, who thinketh himſelf free from thoſe euills, of which we haue ſpoken before, may be perſwaded, that there is not any cauſe, wherefore he ſhould be much confounded: let euery one ſo thinke touching that matter with himſelfe, that there is no cauſe, why he ſhould eſteeme leſſe humbly of himſelf, but is more bound to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in himſelfe, for that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace of God doth euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deliuer him from ſo many and ſo great euills, which if it were not alwayes preſent, who is there that would not fall into the pitt of ſinne, and become
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151937:26"/> worthy of euerlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And ſith he hath eſcaped them through Gods mercy, what thankes then doth he not owe to him? And certes, they haue great cauſe to be confounded, who notwithſtanding they do conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually make an experiment of Gods ſo great mercy towardes them, are neuertheles ſo ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him. And they ought to humble themſelues ſo much the more, the leſſe worthy they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelues of Gods grace: and it is their part to do nothing leſſe in the ſeruice of God, then they would do, if they were drawne and deliuered out of Hell.</p>
                     <p>If euery one would but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this obligation rightly, and vnderſtand that he is able to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God very little for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151937:27"/> of his benefits, he would not be diſcouraged at all, but would comfort himſelfe with that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Prophet, when he ſayth: <hi>Let not the humble, confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he turned away from thee: the poore and needy shall praiſe thy name.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe, if a man hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges, for which he may confound himſelfe before the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, he hath no leſſe cauſe to confound himſelfe before the reſt of the damned, when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth, that many are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to euerlaſting torments, but for one ſinne only. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what is it meet for him to thinke of himſelfe, who knoweth himſelfe to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo many and ſo grieuous ſinnes? And verily he that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth theſe thinges at the hart, ought to go as far beyond
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151937:27"/> them, if he be able, in confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelf, as he goeth beyond them in ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>And if you conſider them who are in <hi>Limbo,</hi> and with how great mercy God hath deliuered you from many dangers, that are wont to happen; and brought you at length to the grace of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, that you might not fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that miſery: there is in truth great cauſe, why you ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your ſo great ingratitude, and waſh it away with teares: and ſo much the more, for that they, who are in <hi>Limbo,</hi> neuer committed any mortall ſinne: and you, as often as you haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it, ſo often haue deſerued hell. And if they for a leſſe ſinne are thruſt down into a deep place or dungeon, with what face dare you liue vpon earth, who haue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151937:28"/> ſo often offended God moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly? And with what eyes dare you contemplate the viſion of God, whereof they are for a far leſſe fault depriued? And if you conſider theſe thinges aright, you will not dare, I know, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould them, who are in Limbo, with attentiue eyes, while you compare your owne ſinnes with theirs.</p>
                     <p>But the conſideration of them, who are in Purgatory, ought to confound vs ſo much the more, for that they, though now in a ſafe place, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of ſo great euills of the world, certaine alſo not to offend God any more, and gotten into an harbour, be neuertheles in paynes: but we are both turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſtormes, and vncertaine of our ſaluation, and what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151937:28"/> of vs at laſt, liuing among moſt crafty, and moſt cruell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, and continuall dangers. And if any be confounded the leſſe, for that he vnderſtandeth, that they are puniſhed deſerued<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their ſinnes: Let him ſo thinke, that ſome are peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there tormented by occaſion of his either example, or bad counſaile, or ſcandall, or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence drawne into ſinne: &amp; that many are detayned &amp; held there the longer, for want of his help by prayers, and other ſuffrages. And let this conſideration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found him, whoſoeuer he be, for that he hath beene an occaſion vnto them of their ſuffering, and paynes, and hath giuen them no help, or little at all towards their eaſe and releaſement: and let him thinke, that their owne faults,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151937:29"/> and his, be the cauſe, that he knoweth not, whether they are to be purged with the fire of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory alone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="exercise">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE IIII. EXERCISE.</hi> Wherein is declared, how we ought to confound our ſelues by the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe thinges, that we ſee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Earth.</head>
                     <p>IF in compariſon of thoſe, who are guilty, we be found more guilty, what ſhal we I pray you, appeare to be before the things, that be not hurtfull at al? For if the conſideration of thoſe who haue ſinned, doth greatly abate and quaile our pride, how much more ought the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151937:29"/> of thoſe thinges humble vs, which haue neuer yet in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſwarued from their Creatours Commandment? The poore Creatures of the Earth, I meane, which hauing but a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue life, do exceedingly conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne our diſobedience, Ingratitude and negligence. For the earth, which produceth and bringeth forth fruit, doth reprehend vs, who are altogeather vnfruitfull, and barraine. And how much doth the water, whiles it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floweth and watreth the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, quencheth the thirſt, and doth thoſe thinges, for which God hath giuen it for the vſe of men, condemne thoſe, who deny it their Creatour, when they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to giue it vnto a poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, crauing it in his name.</p>
                     <p>How doth the fire, whiles
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151937:30"/> it maketh the fleſh ſweet, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory, cenſure the cruelty of thoſe who vnmercifully handle the fleſh of their neighbour? How much doth the Ayre, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually intertayneth our life, vpraid vs of our neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the ſeruice of God, whome but this one thing alone bindeth vs by a moſt ſtrait band to ſerue God? And how much ought the rocks which were rent, (though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible) in the paſſion of Chriſt, to confound our hardnes, and inciuility.</p>
                     <p>Hony is ſweet to the taſt, but we are moſt bitter to God. The ſmell of flowers is pleaſant, but how great is the ſtench of our ſinnes? The plants grow, and raiſe themſelues vpwards, but man, whiles he purſueth baſe &amp; contemptible things, doth abaſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151937:30"/> himſelf euery day more &amp; more. And how much better for him were it to imitate euen the trees heerein, which the more rootes they take, and the deeper they grow in the ground, the more vertue do they draw from them to the bowes: for ſo a man, if he ſhould take deep roote of Humility, would make a great increaſe of vertues. And whome would not the ſeruices of the brute beaſts moue, eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they do it to them, who by their ſinnes haue made themſelus like vnto beaſts? And how much more worthy is he, who hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them ill, or he, who is han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled ill? Or who would not by good right meruaile, that theſe beaſts be obedient to them, who yet are rebellious to the will of God. The ſilly ſheep cloatheth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151937:31"/> you with his skinne, and with his fleece, and nouriſheth you with his fleſh, and when as you ſhould vſe them to the honour of God, you abuſe theſe and other the benefits of God: and while you ſeeke a thouſand wayes to ſatisfy your concupiſcence, you iniury both God, and his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                     <p>The beaſts carry men vpon their backes, and eaſe them wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of their labour, and therein they diligently obey their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, who hath made them for that end: but you on the other ſide do either thinke vpon, or ſeeke after nothing leſſe, then your owne end, whoſe part it were to allow God ſome reſt, if I may ſo ſay, ſith you receaue ſo much comfort and eaſe by his creatures in your labour and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151937:31"/> paynes. We muſt not indeed thinke, that God needeth any reſt, ſith he is the ſupreme felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of himſelfe, and of all thinges els, yet ſuch is his benignity, as he would be thought to reſt in the minds of the iuſt, ſith as he ſayth: <hi>It is his delight to be with the children of men,</hi> though of them he alſo doth not without cauſe complaine in theſe words: <hi>I haue laboured ſuſtayning.</hi> O how great a confuſion ought this word to worke in vs, ſince by our works we occaſion to God this payne, and trauaile, who ought to haue beene to him the cauſe of quiet, and reſt? And therfore it was not ſayd of the brute beaſtes, but of men: <hi>I repent my ſelfe to haue made man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let this, o duſt and aſhes, humble thee: let this draw tears
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151937:32"/> from thyne eyes, and this eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou findeſt that a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the ſeruice done thee cauſeth thee reſt &amp; eaſe, and yet thou doſt not thy ſelfe the like to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. And when thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thy beaſt meate, thinke thus how much more meet it is, that thou ſerue them, then they thee, ſith they haue neuer beene rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, or ingratefull to God, as thou haſt euer beene, and ſtill art.</p>
                     <p>Let the wiſedome of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, who are ſayd to put one eare cloſe to the ground, and ſtop the other with their taile, that they may not heare the voyce of the enchanter, put you in mind of your imprudence, who haue not yet learned to ſtop your eares againſt the tentations of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Againe, let the Ant vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brayd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151937:32"/> you of your ſlouth, and careleſnes, that prepareth thoſe things in Sommer, that may be for her vſe in tyme of winter. And this very thing alon conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth your negligence, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare not now to furniſh your ſelf with thoſe merits, whiles you liue, which you ſhall ſtand moſt in need of after this life.</p>
                     <p>And that you may haue a more ſpatious field, and matter to meditate vpon, conſider the Bees, the ſilly wormes, &amp; other the like creatures, in which you ſhall find many thinges to be wondred at, and which may ſtir vp in you a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of your ſelfe, all which we do purpoſely omit for the auoyding of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity, and for that it was our meaning only, as it were with our finger to point at the matter,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151937:33"/> which euery one may thinke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, leauing deeper and more profound circumſtances to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more excellent wits.</p>
                     <p>And in the meane tyme we are to admoniſh this by the way, that there is in euery creature great matter for our confuſion, if as often as any of them ſhal come to our mind, or repreſent it ſelfe to our eyes, we perſwade our ſelues, that as often we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God our Creatour, we haue deſerued not only to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their vſe and ſeruice, but alſo they ſhould reuenge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs the iniury, that is done to God. And becauſe we ſet that they haue not yet done it, but do vs ſtill ſeruice: how great praiſes and thankeſgiuing, togeather with all humility, &amp; ſubiection, owe we to Gods mercy, &amp; how
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151937:33"/> often ought we to preſent &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our alacrity and readynes of ſeruice vnto him?</p>
                     <p>Neither let a man be afraid to enter into conſideration of ſome other kindes of beaſts, as whiles he either behouldeth a Sow wallowing her ſelfe in the myre, or when he ſeeth a Dog licking vp againe, what he had caſt vp before: let him thinke, that himſelfe is much more fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy then they. And that euery one may iudge thinges aright, &amp; as reaſon would require, it is to be vnderſtand, that nothing of it ſelfe is ill, but as far forth as it is ill in the ſight of God, or by Gods iudgment. Wherefore ſith what we haue ſayd of the Sow, and the Dog (as being thinges vnto them naturall) is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ill before God, the ſame is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151937:34"/> not to be thought to be ill by vs: but this is rather to be conſidered what a thing it is to a ſinner, or what puniſhment he deſerueth, when the ſow doth according to nature, whiles ſhe walloweth in the myre: and he doth againſt his nature, ſith he neither loueth God, nor ſerueth him: and where as he lyeth quietly in ſinne, in how much more filthy myre walloweth he, then doth the Sow? and how much more fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhamefully returneth he (when he goeth backe againe to the ſinne, that he had left before) to his vomit, then doth the Dog? And let that confound him, and ſo much the more, for that he knoweth it to be greatly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God. And therefore let not the facts of ſome vnreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures call any man backe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151937:34"/> from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founding of himſelf, but let euery one be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and aſhamed for his owne miſdeeds, who out of his free will was able, &amp; ought to auoid and ſhunne all euill. And this may ſerue the turne to be ſayd of thoſe creatures, that want rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                     <p>¶ IT now followeth, that we ſay ſomewhat, how the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of reaſonable creaturs, that is, of our neighbours, ought to confound vs. Of theſe ſome are our Superiours, ſome our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, and ſome inferiours. I wil ſay a few thinges touching Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, ſith their authority, &amp; power ouer you, ought ſo to mooue you to ſubmiſſion, and humility, while they are preſent, as vnles you carry your ſelfe very lowly before them, you may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151937:35"/> ſeeme to want the iudgment of reaſon, who conſider not, what manner of perſon, and whoſe they carry. And let it confound you, and ſtrike a great feare into you, for that ſith they are Gods Miniſters, they puniſh you not, who haue offended the diuine Maieſty.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you any thing, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend you or find fault with you, if they chaſtize or mortify you, it ought to ſeeme light, and ſweete vnto you, though to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it may ſeem hard, whether you thinke what you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, or whether you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what you did in former tyms vnder the power of the Diuell, when I ſay, you ſerued ſin vnder his ſtandard, &amp; were vnder his ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in matters not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151937:35"/> for as much as he vſed you for his executioner &amp; hangman, when he moued you to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of murder in thought word, or deed; when through your examples, or perſwaſions many falling into ſinne, went at length down headlong into hell. And if you conſider this ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſeruitude rightly with your ſelfe, all that your Superiours commande you, will ſeem ſweet eſpecially when as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand not to do any thing, but what appertaineth to a quiet life and full of fraternall charity: &amp; you will deeme your ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of thoſe ſuperiours, who be themſelues the Miniſters of the Prince of peace, and be vnto you a great occaſion of meriting life euerlaſting. And thus much touching Superiours.</p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151937:36"/>
                     <p>¶ THE conſideration of your Equalls ſhal confound you thus, if you ſhall thinke your ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be ſayd to be equall to them, to whom you are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour in dignity, or office: for as much as you muſt contemplate their vertues, in which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell you, and are better then you before God. And that you may throughly be perſwaded therin, thinke with your ſelfe thus, that none in what is naught, is better knowne to you, then you are to your ſelfe: for as much as you know certainly of your ſelfe that you thinke and deſire many things, and thoſe naughtily, and that the ſecret ſins of others are not ſo certaine, or well knowne vnto you. And if it be ſo, that you are certaine of your ſinnes, and that you are not certaine of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151937:36"/> others ſinnes, you haue iuſt cauſe to thinke your ſelfe worſe then others, and conſequently inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto them. Wherefore, if you ſee any ſicke, when you are hole and in health your ſelfe, be not proud thereof, but rather conſider with humility, that our Father of heauen handleth him as his beloued child, and that your ſelfe are vnworthy of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall correction, and of his chaſtizment of loue. Againe, if your ſelfe be ſicke, think that you haue deſerued it for your ſinnes; and that others, who enioy good health, haue the benefit of it, as thoſe who ſtand not in need of any great ſatisfaction for their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>If you be rich, feare this ſentence of Chriſt himſelfe: <hi>How hard a matter it is for them, who haue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151937:37"/> and poſſeſſe money, to enter into the Kingdome of heauen.</hi> If your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour be rich, thinke that God hath worthily increaſed his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, for that he is a faythfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſour of his Maiſters goods.</p>
                     <p>If you be poore, aſcribe it to Gods iuſt iudgment, and to your owne deſeruings, who haue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waſted the ſpirituall goods, that God hath beſtowed vpon you, or haue not holpen your poore neighbors with your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance when you were able, and might, or with prayers, or ſuch other like almes. If your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour be poore, thinke that God hath graunted him his deſire, &amp; hath beſtowed a great benefit v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, ſith in pouerty he is become like vnto our Sauiour himſelfe. And if you ſhall carry your ſelfe thus in matters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151937:37"/> your Neighbours, and thinke of them, and of your ſelfe as reaſon ſhall perſwade you, ſhal neuer want matter of confuſion.</p>
                     <p>Neither thinke, that there will be matter wanting alſo in Inferiours: for they though infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in place and office, are not to be contemned, but are rather to be made the more reckoning of, for that God layeth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter burdens vpon them, as being ſtronger, and better able to beare them, while he dealeth gently with you, as with one of a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker body, who cannot (ſuch is your infirmity &amp; weaknes) liue as they do, ſith you haue not ſo much courage, or forces, as you are able both night &amp; day to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much, and many things. And if you thinke, with how great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrity &amp; cheerefullnes of mind
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151937:38"/> moſt of them goe through with their trauailes, and paynes, and with how little they content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in intertayning their life: finally if with their vertue and courage you compare your own coldnes and faintnes of hart, you muſt needs haue great matter of confuſion.</p>
                     <p>When your ſeruants attend vpon you, let this confound you, that when as your ſelfe haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned and forſaken Chriſt, and denyed him due reſpect and honour, yet they follow you, &amp; honorably attend you. Thinke moreouer, that they ſerue you, who are created to enioy heauen and that, while you are in ſinne, and they in Gods grace, you are vnworthy your ſelfe to ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let that example of our Sauiour confound you, when he waſhed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151937:38"/> his diſciples feet: let that be an occaſion of humbling you, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayd: <hi>I came not to be ſerued vnto, but to ſerue.</hi> Finally let their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion confound you before all, for as much as they are made to the Image, and likenes of God, and are ſo deare vnto the eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as he gaue his only Sonne for them.</p>
                     <p>And this ought to confound you before the Infidells them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, when as they be created to the ſame Image, and Chriſt dyed for them all: and you ought to be more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded before them, for this, for that they being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the light of fayth, &amp; of thoſe things, wherewith God is wonte to comfort his, doe neuertheles endure many and great matters in faſtinges, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp; ſuch other like things:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151937:39"/> and you being a Chriſtian, and illuminated with the grace of the holy Ghoſt, and aſſiſted &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen with the gift of fortitude, and ſupported with the loue of God, be ſo wearyed, and do faint in euery the leaſt thing, as you thinke not your ſelfe able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a little pennance: and if you do, you thinke you doe ſome great matter. And therefore let the Infidells ſtir you vp to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and thinke with your ſelf oftentymes this, <hi>that if the vertues had beene done in Tyre and Sidon, that are done in you, they had long ago done pennance in haire-cloath, and ashes,</hi> that is, if the Infidells had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the light of fayth, that you haue, how much more thankfull would they haue been to God, then you are?</p>
                     <p>Wherefore be ſorry, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151937:39"/> you are ſo vnprofitable, and ſuch, as you ought alſo to be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before the Iewes. They did indeed crucify Chriſt once, but yet not knowing him: but you haue crucifyed him ſo often by ſinning, whome you neuertheles knew to ſit on the right hand of his Father in glory. And if they confound you, how much ought euery Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man (thinke you) confound you? For if we giue honour to the image of an Angel for him whome it repreſenteth, in how great honour is it meete to haue him, who carryeth in himſelfe the image of Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and is God by participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is written: <hi>I ſayd, you are Gods, and all Sonnes of the Higheſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And to make an end of thoſe things, that concerne our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, one thing is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151937:40"/> which I thinke greatly hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to the conſeruation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: and this is, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell doth on all handes, and by al the wayes that he can, opugne this Exerciſe, and ſo mightily, as a man needeth to vſe much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, who meaneth not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any hurt from him. And therfore it behooueth vs to haue gotten ſuch an habit, as whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we haue any thing to do, or deale in with our Neighbours, we haue, and carry that reſpect to euery one, as though they were all either our betters, or maiſters, and heare them ſpeake with that attention, as if God himſelfe did ſpeake by them; &amp; our ſpeciall care muſt be, that we beware to prefer our owne iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before theirs. And herein we are wonte to offend for two
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151937:40"/> cauſes.</p>
                     <p>The one is, for that none is a competent and fit Iudge in his owne cauſe: the other is, for that ſometymes out of flatering our ſelues, and often out of ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce we eſteeme not of matters, as we ought, and ſhould do: in ſo much as thereupon the ſubtill, and crafty are recommended for wiſe, and ſuch as ſcoffe at all thinges, are reputed prudent and diſcreet, whereas we are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to deeme the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of them. Wherefore the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureſt and ſafeſt way in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges both of grace, and of nature, is to feare, leaſt we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, and alſo to giue the glory to God in all things, that we ſhal ſee in others, and euer to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete all in the beſt manner. And if they ſhould happen to do any
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151937:41"/> thing, that may not ſeeme aright we muſt not cenſure them (ſith we may not be any others iudge but our owne) but we muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſe the fact, or by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our mind from that matter conſider their good deedes, and compare our owne vices with their vertues, that we may not ouerſlippe, in doing otherwiſe, any degree of confuſion in our ſelues.</p>
                     <p>And therefore if we ſhall ſee any to ſinne mortally, let vs thinke, that he either did it of ignorance, or is already returned into Gods grace by pennance &amp; repentance, and that, that ſinne will be vnto him an occaſion of doing greater pennance heere, &amp; withall of more perfect glory in heauen. And that no occaſion of confounding our ſelues may be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151937:41"/> loſt, we are to obſerue, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, where greater daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are wont to be, that if any ſpeake of meeknes, he call to mind his own paſſions of anger: if mention be made of beautifull things, he remember the fowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his owne ſinnes: if ſpeach be had touching the power and might of great perſonages, he conſider how he is himſelfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and how he can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, euen then alſo, when he laboureth moſt of all to do ſome thing: if a man ſpeake of auarice let him reflect vpon his owne inordinate deſires: if of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let him think vpon his own pride, &amp; ſo in the reſt. When me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of vices, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his owne: and when talke is had of vertues, let him call to remembrance, how he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151937:42"/> wanteth them. And thus doing he ſhall euer haue ſtore of matter of confuſion in himſelf, and that in conuerſation eſpecially, wher there is greateſt danger of omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and forgetting the confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our ſelues.</p>
                     <p>¶ But to come nearer to that confuſion, which ariſeth of the conſideration of our owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, we are to touch ſome few thinges briefly, a more profound and more exact conſideration whereof we leaue to the Reader himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Wherfore let this confound a Prelate, that where Chriſt ſayth: <hi>I giue my life for my sheep:</hi> himſelf is ſo negligent in feeding his owne ſheep, as he knoweth them not all.</p>
                     <p>If he be a Prieſt, let him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found himſelfe, and conſider,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151937:42"/> when as our Sauiour ſayth: <hi>VVho miniſtreth vnto me, let him follow me:</hi> what way he hath held himſelfe &amp; what he hath done with thoſe hands, wherin he is wont in the ſacrifice of Maſſe to hold the very body of our Sauiour.</p>
                     <p>If he be a preacher, let him be confounded, that he exerciſeth the office and place of Chriſt, &amp; yet followeth not the examples of him, whome he preacheth, neither doth the works agreable to that which he ſaith, &amp; let him remember that of the Prophet: <hi>The ſpeaches of our Lord be chast ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> and let him conſider, if he be not a veſſell cleane inough, how great confuſion he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of: and let him feare this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Prophet: <hi>God ſayd vnto the ſinner, wherefore doſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer my iuſtices, and takest vpon thee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151937:43"/> to deliuer my teſtament by thy mouth?</hi> And if S. Paul were afraid, leaſt when he preached to others, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe might become reprobate, what and how great cauſe hath euery Preacher to feare, &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confound himſelfe?</p>
                     <p>Againe, let Schoolemaiſters, and ſuch as teach, be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as thoſe that ſtand moſt in need of confounding themſelues. For the Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>Knowledge puffeth vp.</hi> And if any be proud for his knowledge and learning, for that very cauſe he ought to be moſt of all confounded, for as much as in that behalfe he is more wiſe, &amp; hath a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of himſelfe, then he ſhould.</p>
                     <p>Let the Diſciples &amp; Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers be confounded for their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, who vnles they were, and ſhould be taught, are like to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151937:43"/> the brute beaſts: and alſo for that they both litle profit in learning themſelues, and do as little good to others by that which they knowe, when as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the more they excell in wiſedome, the more ought they to profit many. Finally, for that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> more learned they are, and more increaſe in knowledge, the more they add to their payne, &amp; ſorrow.</p>
                     <p>¶ But the Religious man, ought to be confounded much more before Infidells, and before the reſt of Chriſtians, ſith to him there is not only giuen the light of fayth, but alſo is made parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipant by a ſpecial priuiledge of a life, deuoid of all ſolicitude, &amp; care. Let him be confounded, for that he is choſen out of many thouſands, who if they had been
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151937:44"/> called, would haue beene much more gratefull, and more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God. Let him be alſo confounded, for being ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and diſtracted in the Quire, where the Angells aſſiſt before God: let him be confounded for the ſeruices done him by the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Kitchin, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmary, and els where, who is not worthy either to be ſerued or aſſiſted by any, or who ſhould ſerue or aſſiſt any other him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Let the meate ſet before him in the Refectory to eate, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>found him, which God cauſeth to be prepared &amp; made ready for him without any his payne, or care at all. The apparrell alſo that he weareth, and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouiſion of the houſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for his vſe, togeather with thoſe thinges which men, by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151937:44"/> whoſe trauaile, and paines, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and skill the fieldes and grounds are plowed and ſowen with corne, and through whoſe care all thinges, yeilding forth fruite, are brought to ripeneſſe, and in concluſion returne to his profit. And aboue all things this ſhould confound him moſt, for that he is called Gods ſeruant, to whome neuertheles he oftentims becometh an enemy. Which ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily is a name in which the moſt B. Virgin did after a ſort glory, when ſhe called her ſelfe Gods Hand-maid.</p>
                     <p>Againe, let nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found a Religious man more, then Gods houſe, wherein he dwelleth as a child of his, when as notwithſtanding he is ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perfection of his Father of heauen, &amp; as many ſteps as he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151937:45"/> hath made therein, in ſo many as it were waues is he plunged in the ſea, and gulfe of confuſion. For if <hi>holynes beſeemeth the houſe of our Lord;</hi> how doth God endure iniquity in it? Or why be not the cold, and indeuout thruſt out of the houſe of prayer? Againe, if Gods houſe be ſuch a place, as the great both King &amp; Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> chooſeth <hi>rather to dwell in it, then any where els,</hi> and holdeth him ſelfe for contemned and outcaſt in it, for the bliſſe of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how great ought the confuſion of that man to be, who abideth in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will? Or if he ſtayeth willingly there, is neuertheles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull to God, for that his ſo great a benefit?</p>
                     <p>Moreouer let al the Ceremonies of Religion confound him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he either vnderſtandeth not
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151937:45"/> what they meane, or marketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, or thinketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burdenous, or els careth not for them, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profiting him.</p>
                     <p>Let him be confounded, when he asketh almes for the loue of God, ſith it is a matter of ſingular priuiledge: and let him thinke, what a matter it is that God, as one who ſtandeth in need, maketh himſelfe a debtour for him vnto them, who giue him any thing when he beggeth, and hath put him in truſt with his treaſure. And if he hath at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tyme not ſpent thoſe thinges. that are giuen him for Gods ſake to that vſe, for which he craued them, let him he confounded as ſacrilegious, who depriueth God of that, which others at his intreaty did giue to God. Let him thinke, that when he beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151937:46"/> as a poore beggar, vnles he be poore in mind, and intention he craueth vnder a falſe title: &amp; if he asketh of curioſity, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which Gods will is he ſhould do, he is a deceauer, &amp; robbeth the neighbour of his money, after the manner of thoſe who begge with falſe &amp; forged Licences.</p>
                     <p>Finally let him be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for that when he asketh in the name of God, he doth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Angells, who as Gods meſſengers do euer beg of men; of ſome to relieue and help the poore, of others to pardon and forgiue the iniuries don to them, and of others to giue the honour and glory that they owe to God. And when he ſhall receaue almes let him be confounded, for that he is ingrate, and thankles both
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151937:46"/> to God, and to his Neighbour. And by ſo doing, when he is to aske any thing he will beginne to be confounded, as one, who vnderſtandeth and knoweth wel how great an obligation it is, whereunto the almes receaued bindeth him, and he will craue only what is neceſſary, ſith the greater his band, and obligation ſhal be, the more he ſhall take.</p>
                     <p>And when he goeth in pilgrimage, let him beware, that this thought enter not into his mind, that he thinke himſelfe to lead an Apoſtolicall life, but let him rather thinke, that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him for his pennance. And if he be of the number of the recluſe, or of ſuch as liue in Cloiſters, let him thinke, that it was our Lords will to remoue him, as an vnruly and vntamed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151937:47"/> beaſt, from the conuerſation and company of men.</p>
                     <p>¶ If he be a King, or a Prince let him be confounded, for that he is in that ſtate, which our B. Sauiour fled from, when the Iewes would haue created him a King. And meruayle it is, that any dare take that charge vpon him, which Chriſt himſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, vnles he peraduenture take it for his Croſſe, and vndergo it for the loue of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>¶ Let owners, maiſters &amp; ſuch as be poſſeſſed of Lands, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded for being very diligent in gathering &amp; heaping vp rents and reuenewes, and as negligent on the other ſide in puniſhing publique ſinnes. And let them be afrayd for vſing money &amp; other goods, as their owne, and for not remembring him, at whoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151937:47"/> handes they haue receaued and had all. Let them be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for making great eſteeme of themſelues, when they relieue the poore with almes, whiles they thinke not, that they giue what is anothers, and render vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God what is his, and that God doth them a great good turne, and pleaſure in that, in which they thinke themſelues to doe a benefit. And if they ought to confound themſelues euen then, when they giue alms, how much more are they to do it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſpend their money in vaine, and waſtefull vſes.</p>
                     <p>¶ Againe, a Knight muſt thinke, that he hath taken the ſword vpon him for the defence of Gods holy Church, Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and Apoſtolicall, and for the aduancement of Gods honour.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151937:48"/> And if the deſire of his own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour take away the memory, &amp; remembrance of the other, and he preferre his owne honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that of God, what is he els then a perſecutor of the Church of Chriſt, and his Ghoſpell? And therefore let him be confounded as faythles, and falſe to God, and let him thinke, though he be held &amp; deemed for a man of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour amongſt men, that he is yet but a ſlaue of ſin, &amp; for that cauſe by the iudgment of God, and of his Saints in no ſort worthy of honour, but one ordeyned, and deputed to be puniſhed in Hell for euer.</p>
                     <p>Let ſeruants be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for being ſo ſollicitous in gayning the fauour of their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: which diligence if they had vſed in the ſeruice of God,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151937:48"/> how much ſooner had they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more true fauour at his hands, for to ſerue him then others?</p>
                     <p>¶ Let Iudges thinke, with what ſeuerity they pronounce ſentence againſt the guilty, and let them bee confounded for not apprehending nor fearing the iudgment of God, of which it is written: <hi>Moſt hard iudgment shall bee to them, who rule and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let the Aduocates bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, that though they pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize, and defend other mens cauſes, yet they are very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent touching their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: neyther let them bee proude for that they ſee others to need their helpe: for they ſtand themſelues in need of the help of many alſo, euen in thoſe things, that appertaine to their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151937:49"/> ſoules.</p>
                     <p>Let the Phiſitians bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, when they conſider, how they handle their patients; And if they knew, when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſhould fal ſicke, with how great diligence would they ſeek &amp; procure the recouery of their health? Let them alſo thinke vpon the wounds of their ſoules, and therat bee confounded, for that when as they bee called phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, yet they are more skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in procuring of their owne ſicknes by ſin, then in putting it away.</p>
                     <p>Let Merchants be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the care, which they vſe in buying cheap, and in ſelling deare, and for thoſe things that they remayne ignorant of; and know not how to buy the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, which is giuen
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151937:49"/> 
                        <hi>Gratis:</hi> and yet they buy Hell, which both coſteth them deare, and is poſſeſſed with paine.</p>
                     <p>¶ And to come to the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſmen of the common wealth, let the Taylors be confounded and aſhamed, who take ſo much care and ſtudy in making other mens apparell, while themſelues are notwithſtanding very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in conſeruing their owne garment of innocency, which they receyued in Baptiſme.</p>
                     <p>Let the Shoomakers be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, who though they be able to enter &amp; pierce moſt hard leather with their alls, will not for all that ſuffer Gods inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to enter into their minds.</p>
                     <p>¶ And whoſe wit may ſerue him to ſpeake of the ſtate of Women as it deſerueth, in theſe tymes eſpecially, in which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151937:50"/> the vanity of them is growne to ſo great an exceſſe.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore let Virgines be confounded for hauing thought vpon marryage. For though it bee a thing lawfull, yet how much better is it for them to be contented with Chriſt for their ſpouſe alone: and they would indeed content themſelues with Chriſt alone, if they ſhould loue him with all the loue they are able.</p>
                     <p>Let the married be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for being ouer diligent, and curious in decking themſelues, and in waſting and ſpending ſo much tyme and money in that reſpect: and contrariwiſe for being moſt negligent, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in putting on Chriſt. When they put their chaines of gold about their neccks, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151937:50"/> that Chriſts chaines were of yron, and were put vpon him for his ignominy, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. When they put on their bracelets vpon their armes, let them thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the binding of Chriſtes hands. When they cloth themſelues in their gorgeous &amp; coſtly array, let them remember that Chriſt had a garmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> moſt ignominious put vpon his back. (And let not onely Women, but men alſo be confounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> who, when as they weare ſuch gay &amp; coſtly apparell, do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſwere Chriſts reproches, as they ought.) And if they would but conſider the workes of their hands they would, no doubt pull their rings of their fingers, as from members that are not worthy the ſetting forth, ſith they haue done works vnworthy Chriſtian women.</p>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151937:51"/>
                     <p>Let widowes be confounded, who ſo grieuouſly lament the death of their husbands, for that ſith God hath taken away from them all the impediments of perfect Loue towards him, they be ſo thankles for ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; in ſo much as they may ſeeme to giue to vnderſtand, that they were better content with the creature, then with the Creatour; and that they in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap> no reckoning of God by taking the death of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands impatiently. For they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that their husbands be taken from them: but indeed God hath much more iuſt cauſe to complaine of them, who ſeeth himſelf to be contemned by them. And therefore let them be confounded, and let them heare how our Lord complaineth of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151937:51"/> them in theſe words: <hi>They haue forſaken me, the fountaine of the lyuing waters, and haue digged themſelues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed cisterns, which are not able to hold water.</hi> And that: <hi>VVhat ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity haue they found in me, for that they haue estranged themſelues from me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this may be inough touching different ſtates, leaſt we may ſeeme to exceede and go beyond the bounds of our intended breuity: and withall for that it is an eaſy matter, of what we haue ſayd to make a coniecture of other things, and ro ſet them downe. And if any will diligently conſider thoſe things, that we haue remembred before, he may euer haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of confounding himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>And now to come to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward powers: be thou, O Man,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151937:52"/> confounded touching thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. For ſith thou knoweſt, that thy Creatour hath giuen thee this wonderfull power for this, that thou mighteſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him both euer and ſweetly; yet thou haſt lodged many baſe and contemptible things in it, and therein haſt ſo occupied and buſied it, as thou haſt ſcarce tyme or leaſure to remember him who gaue thee it, in ſo much as it ſerueth nothing at al leſſe then it doth the Creatour. Wherefore be thou confounded and aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for that thou haſt abuſed it to the iniury of thy Lord; and for that whereas thou art often put in mind by the Church, who thou art, by aſhes euery yeare put vpon thy head, and by ſaying of theſe words: <hi>Remember man, that thou art duſt, and to duſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151937:52"/> thou shalt returne:</hi> and of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, one while of thine end, when it ſayth: <hi>Remenber the laſt things:</hi> and another while of thoſe things, that Chriſt ſuffred for thy ſake, when it ſayth: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my pouerty, and my tranſgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, the gall, and wormewood:</hi> And of other things often at other tymes; yet thou ſeemeſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member nothing leſſe then theſe and the like, and haſt iuſt cauſe to weepe, and to ſay with the Prophet: <hi>My ſoule refuſeth to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted:</hi> I <hi>was mindfull of God,</hi> and, <hi>I was delighted:</hi> and, <hi>to be confounded the more, for that thou haſt ſometymes recreated thy ſelfe in the obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And now to come to the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, how large a ſcope of confuſion doth repreſent it ſelfe in it to thee, which for as much as it vnderſtandeth that it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151937:53"/> is created to this end, that it might vnderſtand the ſupreme God, doth notwithſtanding ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke not onely vpon vaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and tranſitory things, but alſo moſt bad: and is finally occupied in thoſe things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it knoweth it ſhould not attend. Thou haſt, certes, iuſt cauſe to weepe, and to lament this ill of thine, with all the confuſion, thou canſt poſſibly procure, and ſtirre vp in thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>And what ſhall we ſay of the Will, wherewith, when as thou ſhouldeſt loue God aboue all things, thou haſt affected thoſe things, which it is a ſhame to thinke of, much more to ſpeake? What (I ſay) ſhall I ſay of thee, o blind Will, which haſt preferred the pleaſure of thy
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151937:53"/> ſenſes before the goods of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Which when the ſweet charity and loue of God might place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the Seraphims, the foule and filthy loue of the world hath throwen down into hell. Thy powers, O ſoule, ought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to confound the, in which thou haſt ſo fowle an image of God.</p>
                     <p>Thou mayeſt indeed, and oughteſt with, greife to blame them with theſe words: <hi>Behold Adam is become as it were one of vs:</hi> and to complayne of them in this manner: <hi>VVho, O powers, who O imare of God,</hi> I ſay, <hi>hath maried you? who, O Memory, hath ſpoyled thee of the memory of God? VVho, o Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, hath depriued thee of thy iudgment? VVho, O VVill, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued thee?</hi> O how fitly, O ſoule, may this be ſayd of thee: <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151937:54"/> Princes are become as Rams, not hauing pastures to feede in?</hi> For as Rams, when they find not paſtures, thy powers, as though they had not any paſturing in God, haue ſought out impoiſoned paſtures to feed in, &amp; for that cauſe their forces faile them, and therefore thou oughteſt to be exceedingly confounded in thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Let vs paſſe ouer to the Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes. God hath indeed giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee eyes, that by beholding the beauty of his creatures, thou mighteſt loue him in all and euery thing, and giue him thankes for al: but thou contrariwiſe makeſt hauocke &amp; waſt of all things, that thou ſeeſt, eyther as one raging and madde with anger, or deſiring with a couetous minde. And therefore when as thine eyes ought to bee euer before Gods
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151937:54"/> 
                        <hi>(As the eyes of the handmaid in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of her miſtres)</hi> they do often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Baſilisks, which with their ſight do kill whatſoeuer they looke vpon.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore bee thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, for hauing conuerted the light, that hath been giuen thee, into darknes: for ſhutting thine eares againſt holy inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and opening them to heare murmurings and detractions: for accurſing men with thy to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, wherwith thou ſhouldſt haue bleſſed them: for hauing accuſtomed thy ſelfe to this, that nothing might be vnſpleaſant to thy ſmell, and yet thou feeleſt not the loathſome ſtench of ſyn: And finally for that all ſeemeth hard to thee, if thou were to ſuffer any thing for Chriſt, and that againe ſweet, which thou endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151937:55"/> for the world. Wherefore lament the euills and miſeries of thy Senſes, and let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof draw and wreſt from thee humble, and harty teares and thoſe full of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>And if al this be not inough let thine Head confound thee, for that it is not yet pricked with thorns: let the haires of thy head co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found thee that they are not yet pulled of: let thine hands, and feet confound thee, that they are not pierced through with nayles: finally, let the reſt of thy members confound thee for that they cannot bee moued, but by the vertue and power of God, and yet thou haſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſt with thy feet, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him with thy hands and works, and hurt him with thy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151937:55"/> tongue.</p>
                     <p>Finally, if thou conſider the matter with an vpright iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou art alone vnto thy ſelfe a great matter of confuſion. For there is not any thing in thee, whereof, if thou diligently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke thy ſelfe, thou oughteſt not greatly to be confounded. And if there be many things with in thee, which thou vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, euen for that alone thou haſt moſt great cauſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, for that thou knowſt not thy ſelfe throughly. For what thy ſoule is, or what it hath in it, or how it is vnited to thy body, or how it is to be ſeuered from thy body, if thou demaund of thy ſelfe, I know thou canſt not anſwere me. And if thou be ſo ignorant in things appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thy ſelfe, how ignorant,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151937:56"/> I pray thee, muſt thou needs be in matters that concerne others? This in the meane tyme is true, that both in thoſe things that thou knoweſt touching thy ſelf, and in thoſe that thou knoweſt not, there is preſented thee great and abundant matter of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>And if any ſhould in this place obiect vnto me, that there is not found matter of confuſion in good workes, but in the bad onely; I would ſtand in denyall thereof, for as much as I am of opinion, that we ought to be confounded in our good works alſo, for this; for that we be ſo weake to good, &amp; again ſo prone &amp; ready to yll, as it is more to be wondred, that any good could proceede out of ſo corrupted a nature, then a Roſe to grow out
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151937:56"/> of a roſe-buſh. For it is naturall for a roſe-buſh to bring forth roſes; but mans nature alone cannot of it ſelfe produce a good or perfect worke, for as much as nothing can be pleaſing to God without his grace. Wherefore he, that meruaileth at a Roſe growing amongſt thorns, ought to wonder much more, that any good is done of himſelfe, and to be ſo much the more confounded for that he ſeeth, that God, as in a barraine ſoile, and ſuch as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re worthy to be deſtroyed with ſalt, for the moſt great ſins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited againſt God, worketh wonderfull matters, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth &amp; continueth to manure and husband it. And therefore we may, and ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, not onely of our bad works, but of our good alſo. For
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151937:57"/> if we do any good, God hath begun, proſecuted, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the ſame in vs: and it is our part, as a thing peculiar &amp; proper to vs alone, to confound and humble our ſelues more and more, who haue ſo often reſiſted God, and haue through his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and mercy eſcaped that puniſhment, which we haue ſo many wayes moſt worthily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="exercise">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE V. EXERCISE.</hi> Wherein is deliuered, how we may be confounded by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of Celeſtial things.</head>
                     <p>I Scarce know how to ſpeake of matters of Heauen, who
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151937:57"/> haue byn ſo far from deliuering what was fit to be ſayd touching earthly things, in which there is miniſtred vnto vs ſo great and abundant matter of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. There is indeed euen in the only contemplation of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heauens, great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of confuſion, if we compare the diſorder of our owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with ſo admirable an order. For what ſhould I ſay of the Planets, which we know euer both to receaue a vertue from their ſuperiors, and to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate that againe, which they haue receiued, continually to their inferiors. And of all things it is man alone, who is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment vnto himſelfe, that he receiueth not the benefit of the influences from aboue; &amp; when he receiueth them, he neglecteth
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151937:58"/> to impart the ſame vnto others. And whereas all the Heauens &amp; the ſtars receaue light from the Sunne; man alone refuſeth to cloath himſelfe with the light of iuſtice, and as it is written, loueth darkenes, more then light.</p>
                     <p>And if we contemplate the Angells, how much I pray you, will their purity, and innocency confound vs? how great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion ought this to ſtrike into vs, that we neglect their ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary counſails, giuen vs with ſo great wiſdome and charity? Words will indeed fayle me, in my deſire and willingnes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our confuſion, as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, whether we compare our tepidity to the loue of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims, or our ignorance with the knowledg of the Cherubims.</p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151937:58"/>
                     <p>And if any may peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thinke the Angells ouer high to compare our duſt, and aſhes with them; let vs come lower to the Saints, who ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes conſiſted of fleſh and blood as we do; neyther was humane fraylty vnto them, as being men, an impediment, but that they wrought many great, and wonderfull works for the honour of God. And therefore let the deeds of the men of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, confound the works of the men on earth: let the conſtancy and courage of the martyrs in their torments confound our inconſtancy in good purpoſes, and our infirmity and faintnes of hart. Let the penance of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and their auſterity of life confound our pleaſures, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacy, and eaſe: let the Virgin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:151937:59"/> purity, and eſpecially that of our Sauiour, and his immaculate Mother, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found our turpitude. And this aboue the reſt, for that, where we be moſt obliged to the moſt ſacred Virgin for the education and bringing vp of her ſonne, who was to be offred for vs to the eternall Father v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Croſſe; we neuer can in the leaſt requite ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, but are withal vngratefull; in ſo much as we ſhould not dare for very ſhame to craue any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy at his hands.</p>
                     <p>But who can be ſufficiently confounded in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of Chriſt, or what depth of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion may ſerue the turne here, when a man conſidereth Chriſt, whom he hath for his only reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; refuge, ſo to haue been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>d by himſelfe as our Sauiour
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151937:59"/> might worthily ſay: <hi>I am caſt from the face of thin eyes.</hi> For thy tepidity ſlouth &amp; drowſynes hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his feete: thy inobedience hath opened his ſyde: thy works haue nayled his hands faſt: thy tongue hath giuen him gall to drinke: finally, thy pride hath crowned him with thornes. And to ſpeake in one word, there is not any thing in Chriſt, which when thou ſeeſt, ought not worthily to confound thee. And therefore it is written: <hi>Let the proud be confounded, for that they haue done iniquity againſt me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And what ſhall we now ſay of the confuſion which the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of the moſt ſacred Trinity cauſeth. Or how great ſhal the confuſion be before God, if it was ſo great before the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells? With what eyes ſhall you
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151937:60"/> dare to looke vpon the Eternall Father, who haue not only not receyued his only ſonne, by him ſent to recouer the inheritance, that you haue prodigally wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and ſpent, but alſo forced him to dye the death of the Croſſe? What accompt will you make for the inheritance, where with you were put in truſt? And what will you anſwere for thoſe both temporall, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall goods, which you haue had and receyued of him?</p>
                     <p>Againe, what can you haue to ſay to the Sonne of God, who ſuffered all for you? He may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed worthily ſay to men: Let them be confounded, for that, when as I God came down from heauen into earth for their ſake, and vouchſafed to become man for the ſauing of their ſoules, yet
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151937:60"/> they will not leaue their filth of ſinne. Be thou confounded, O man, ſith I loued thee firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou louedſt me: and ſeeing I ſerued thee, before thou ſeruedſt me. O hard and yron harts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who, though they ſee me bound to the piller, ſcourged &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for loue, had yet rather be bound to ſyn, then to cleaue to me, and to preferre the loue of me before that of the world: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they vnderſtand, how cruelly and vnmercyfully they are ſcourged of the Diuel, whiles they be fettered in the bands of ſyn.</p>
                     <p>I gaue vnto man my very bowells, whieh he might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and cleaue faſt vnto, as to a moſt firme and ſtable piller, &amp; yet he maketh no accompt of me, and followeth thoſe things,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151937:61"/> that worthily condemne him before me. O ingratitude of men! o ſenſeles minds of men! the bruit beaſts do me ſeruice, the trees &amp; plants praiſe me, and of al things man alone acknowledgeth me not, but like a mad dog, who bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his maiſter, riſeth againſt me, beeing worthy whome the earth ſhould open, and ſwallow down.</p>
                     <p>Be thou confounded, o man, for whome I became a meeke Lambe, and ceaſe thou at length to be a fierce and raging Lion, I imbrace and loue thee with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and thou whippeſt me with the ſcourge of deſire; and when I ſet thee forthwith the precious margarites of humility, thou crowneſt my head with the pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thorns of pride. Let men at length vnderſtand, that they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151937:61"/> haue receyued goods, not to be ſhut and locked vp in cheſts, but to be giuen out to the poore. Let them conſider, how hartily and affectuouſely I loue them, whome I, by them being caſt into priſon, will deliuer from out of the dungeon of hell: and whome they ceaſe not to crucify with ingratitude, I by charity will bring backe againe into the way of charity.</p>
                     <p>Be thou confounded, o man, whome when the Angells be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, they then contemne, and the Diuells deceyue, and in my ſight condemne. Be thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, I ſay, &amp; feare my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and vnles thou be heere confounded, and bewaile thy ſyns, a great, and bitter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion attendeth thee. Whome would it not confound, for that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151937:62"/> I God, and Lord of all do, like the hunter, contynually ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and purſue men, that they, who coſt me ſo dearly, may not in any caſe periſh, while they ſtil euer fly from me, as from an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenomed ſerpent? Why do they not feare me, and my iudgments? Why do they not chang, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their liues, who knowe neyther the houre, nor day of their death?</p>
                     <p>And what anſwere will you make to the holy Ghoſt? or with what face will you dare to ſpeake vnto him, who haue ſhut the gates of your ſoule often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and haue ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and wickedly thruſt him out, that you might admit and receyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the Diuell?</p>
                     <p>Be ye confounded, o wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched men, whome notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151937:62"/> God hath created to be his children, who is in heauen; yet you ſcarce euer do workes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your heauenly Father. There is in him endles meeknes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, and he is euer ready to remit and pardon ſynnes: but you, full of iniquity, do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not forgiue the iniuryes done you, but do further iniure thoſe, who haue neuer deſerued any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill at your hands. There is in him ſurpaſſing goodnes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth good euen to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes, while he euer conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them: but you alſo do euill to your friends. There is in him euerlaſting wiſdome, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull prouidence, wherewith he gouerneth all things: but in you there is an extraordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ouerturne and deſtroy all things, ſo you may raigne, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151937:63"/> be kings alone. And therefore our Lord reprehendeth you by his Prophet in theſe words: <hi>VVill you dwell alone vpon the earth?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
                     <p>MATTER faileth me not, but tyme, and therefore this may ſerue the turne for the prudent Reader, who of a few things may gather many more, and thereof reape the fruite of Confuſion, and of humbling himſelfe, eſpecially if he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelfe in them continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and diligently: which euery one ought to do with the greater care and circumſpection, for that therein conſiſteth the greateſt part of ſpirituall profit, for the knowing, and acknowledging
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151937:63"/> of our great infirmity, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                     <p>And they who haue attayned this, and haue begon to build v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch a foundation before lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may with ſafty proceede in building, and go on forward in that ſpirituall edifice: and they that build their worke in any other manner then this which we haue ſaid, when they haue once raiſed it high, it is wont to fal to the ground againe. For it hapneth, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of prayer, which are wont to help to the furthering, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of vertues, vnles they be ſupported and conſerued by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, do degenerate into falſe, counterfaite, &amp; deceitfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations. So the deſires of good things be indeed good, but if we ſo aſcribe them vnto our ſelues,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151937:64"/> as we acknowledge them not for Gods benefits, we both grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly deceaue our ſelues, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly build any ſtrong matter vpon ſo weake a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore who meaneth to haue his works perfect, muſt both begin them with confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſerue them by it: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt he be ſo hardy as to proceed in any thing without confuſion accompayning the ſame. And ſo it will follow, that he, who neuer forgetteth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and humble himſelfe, ſhal neuer be forſaken of God: <hi>who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſpiſeth a contrite &amp; humbled hart,</hi> but willingly conuerſeth with the humble and lowly. And this we may ſay is the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which whoſoeuer ſhall haue vpon his backe, he ſhall
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151937:64"/> neuer be ſhut out from the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding feaſt.</p>
                     <p>This is the badge and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Gods children: this he muſt haue and weare, who hath a wil to follow Chriſt, becauſe he did weare it himſelfe, when he ſaid: My baſhfulnes is al the day long againſt me: and the confuſion of my face hath couered me ouer &amp; ouer. And if confuſion did alſo couer Chriſts face ouer and ouer, who was the looking glaſſe of the Angells, and the glory of the Saints: why ſhould it not couer the face of a ſynner ouer &amp; ouer? Or who but he that hath it on, dare come into the ſight of God, ſith it is written: <hi>Let them, who detracte me, be clad with shame: and let them be couered ouer and ouer with their confuſion, as with a doublet?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Marke further, what our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151937:65"/> Lord ſayth: <hi>Vpon whome shall my ſpirit rest, but vpon the humble, and contrite in hart, and dreading my ſpeaches?</hi> And if God confound the iuſt, the ſynner muſt not thinke to eſcape, eſpecially ſith not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly the iuſt on earth, but alſo the Saints in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are clad with this garment. And no leſſe maybe vnderſtood by the words of the Goſpell, when they ſpeake vnto Chriſt in the day of iudgment in theſe words: <hi>when did we ſee thee an hungred, and we ſed thee?</hi> That is, they ſpeake as men aſtoniſhed, and wondring, that by ſo little works they haue merited ſo great rewards.</p>
                     <p>And the ſame is ſufficiently inſinuated by <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> when he bringeth them in ſaying thus, <hi>Lord, why haſt thou prepared ſo great and ſuch glory for vs?</hi> And if this Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151937:65"/> raiſeth vs vp into heauen, it is reaſon that we imbrace it here, and that we commit our ſelues vnto it, as to a ſure anker in a dangerous tempeſt: and that we doubt not, but if we rely v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, we ſhall get ouer the ſtormy and dangerous ſea of this miſerable life, and in the end, through Gods mercy, ariue to the ſafe port of Heauen. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:151937:66"/>
                  <head>A SHORT RVLE How to liue well.</head>
                  <div n="6" type="exercise">
                     <head>THE VI. EXERCISE.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>Of the things, that man is to know for the ſauing of his ſoule. <hi>CHAP. I.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Chriſtian man, that wil lead a good life for the ſauing of his ſoule, muſt know three things. 1. His end,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151937:66"/> for which he was made and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 2. The meanes, neceſſary &amp; profitable for the attayning of his end. 3. The manner, and way, how practiſe the ſame.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <head>Of the End of man. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THE laſt end of man is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting blyſſe. For he was created by God to be foreuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in paradiſe: And his ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, ſo it be free from ſtayne of ſyn, ſhall be conducted by his good Angell into heauen, there for all eternity to enioy the viſion of God. And after the worlds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation, man ſhall enioy his end of beatitude wholy, both in ſoule and body, which ſhall be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151937:67"/> againe reſuſcitated and conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſoule, to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſoueraigne Iudge; and of him to receyue the reward of life euerlaſting. But, alas, many there be, who neuer ſhall ariue to this end, for which they were created, becauſe they put not in practiſe the meanes requiſite for the ſauing of their ſoules. It is therefore good and needfull to know, what theſe meanes be, &amp; how they are to be practiſed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <head>Of the meanes to come to our End. <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>SOME meanes there be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary towards the attayning of our laſt end: &amp; ſome againe very profitable for
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151937:67"/> the ſame reſpect. The neceſſary meanes be principally three. 1. A man muſt haue faith, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in God, and further belieue al that which God hath reuealed vnto vs by his Holy Catholike Church, becauſe it is infallible verity: he muſt haue knowledge of the things, that concerne his ſaluation which are declared in the Catechiſme; whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, how maynly it impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all to know and vnderſtand the principall points of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrine comprehended in the ſaid Catechiſme.</p>
                        <p>As touching God he muſt know, that he is omnipotent, moſt wiſe, moſt good, moſt iuſt: that he hath euer been, and euer ſhall be: that he is euery where: that he ſeeth and knoweth all things: that there is but one God
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151937:68"/> in three perſons, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, who be al of one and the ſame Nature, of the ſame Omnipotency, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Goodnes, and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                        <p>Alſo that the ſecond Perſon, in Trinity, which is the Sonne of God, became man and tooke mans fleſh in the wombe of the ſacred Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; that he hath redeemed vs by his moſt paynefull death.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt hope in God, becauſe he is our ſupreme and ſoueraigne good.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt loue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things ſeeing that for his ſoueraigne bounty and goodnes he is moſt worthy of our Loue. And the loue of God is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated and practiſed in obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151937:68"/> of his Commaundements, and of the Commandements of the Church, and in abſtayning from all ſyn, and in particular from mortall, becauſe the ſame is wholy oppoſite to him, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth vs abſolutly from our end. And we muſt loue our neighbour, as our ſelues, for the loue of God.</p>
                        <p>Other meanes there be, that may alſo greatly help vs toward the more eaſy, &amp; more aſſured at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of our end. Such be, 1. To exerciſe ſome things in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when we riſe, afterwards in the reſt of the day following, and at night when we go to bed. 2. To examine our Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience euery day. 3. To frequent the holy Sacraments of confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; Communion. 4. To heare Maſſe euery day, or as often
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151937:69"/> as we find the oportunity, but eſpecially on ſundays and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies. 5. To frequent vocall, and mentall prayer. 6. To be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in hearing of Sermons, and the explication of the Chriſtian doctrine. 7. To be frequent in reading of ſpirituall books. 8. To giue our ſelues to the exerciſe of al vertue &amp; good works &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="chapter">
                        <head>Of the manner, how to practiſe the aforeſaid meanes well. <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>MANY there be, who know right well, what they ought to do for the ſauing of their ſoules, but they haue not the knowledge, how to practiſe the ſame: and therefore the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151937:69"/> ſubiect of this ſhort and ſpirituall Treatiſe, ſhall be to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify the manner of practiſing thoſe meanes well which may conduct vs to our end. And for the eaſier orders ſake, we wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide it into two parts; In the former wherof ſhall be declared the manner of the pactiſing of diuers ſpirituall exerciſes, heere after mentioned: And in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we will giue inſtructions, how we ought to demeane and carry our ſelues towards God &amp; his Saints, towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and towardes our ſelues.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="exercise">
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151937:70"/>
                     <head>The former part, of the Way to lyue well. THE VII. EXRCISE.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>What we ſhould do in the Morning <hi>CHAP. I.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>A good Chriſtian as ſoone as he awaketh in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, muſt bleſſe himſelfe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſigne of the holy Croſſe, that therewith he may defend himſelfe as a buckler againſt all his enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es, and whatſoeuer euill may befall him the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. That done, let him raiſe his mind vp to God, yealding him his firſt thought. And being
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151937:70"/> vp, he muſt practiſe foure things 1. He muſt giue God thanks for al benefits receyued of him in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and in particular for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing him that night from all euill.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt offer vnto God his both body and ſoule to ſerue him, and conſecrate vnto him all his actions, with an intent and purpoſe to do them to his greater honour and glory.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. He muſt make a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe &amp; firme reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a better life then he hath lead the dayes paſt, and of abſtayning from all ſyns, &amp; in particular from thoſe, whereunto the findeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt inclined.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He muſt make petition to God, that he would pleaſe to take him into his protection and ſafegard: and craue grace that he
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151937:71"/> may be able to put his good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in practiſe, and to do all his good works moſt acceptable to the diuine will.</p>
                        <p>It will be very good alſo to the ſame effect, to implore the aide and aſſiſtance of the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Virgin Mary, of our good Angell, Patrone, and other Saints, for as much as they can do very much with God, and may eaſily obtayne what we demaund. And this done let him ſay a <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Aue.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <head>What we are to do at Night. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>BEFORE we take our reſt, it profiteth very much. 1. To be thankfull to God for his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, &amp; namely for thoſe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151937:71"/> which we haue receyued that very day.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To make an examen of our conſcience in the manner, which we ſhall ſet down afterwards.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To aske of God, that he will vouchſafe to preſerue &amp; keepe vs that night from ſicknes, from ſodaine death, from euill dreames, diſquiet, and from all offending him. To recommend our ſelues alſo to the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin mother of God, and to our good Angell, &amp; other Saints ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our deuotion, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſay ſome prayer, as we did in the morning.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Then to take holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with deuotion and compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of hart, for as much as by the prayers of the Church it hath great effect to purge and waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way veniall ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <pb n="120" facs="tcp:151937:72"/>5. Beeing laid downe in bed, to endeauour to fall a ſleepe with ſome good thought or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our mind.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <head>What it is meete for vs to do in the day tyme; <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IN the day tyme it is good to exerciſe foure things. 4. To take heed we ſpend not the tyme vnprofitably: for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world ſo precious, as the tyme, that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs (as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth) for foure reſpects: to wit, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne pardon for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: to do penance, and ſatisfy the payn, that is due to our ſyns: to procure and increaſe Gods grace; and to merit eternal glory.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <pb n="121" facs="tcp:151937:72"/>2. When we are to begin any worke, that we offer it to God, adreſſing it to his honour, and crauing his grace to begin it well.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Oftentimes to renewe the good purpoſes, we made in the morning, ſith ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing thereof, cauſeth vs to ſtand more vpon our guard, and to be more preſent to our ſelues. And if we find, that we haue fayled in the execution thereof, to be ſory therfore, and craue new help of God, that we may do better for the reſt of the day to come.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Oftentymes alſo to lift vp our mindes to God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that he is euer preſent with vs, beholding and obſeruing all our thoughts, deſires, intentions, words and actions. And this
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151937:73"/> recollection may be practiſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tyme we heare the clocke ſtrike. And then alſo it would be good to bleſſe our ſelues: for ſo doing we do three things. 1. We inuoke Gods aſſiſtance, in all things which we intend to do: &amp; the making of the ſigne of the Croſſe is a prayer. 2. We deuote our ſelues to God, and we offer him our works; for that this ſigne is an act of oblation. 3, We arme our ſelues againſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſaults of our capitall enemy: for this ſigne of the Croſſe is a kind of exorciſme againſt the Diuell himſelfe, and whatſoeuer other euill alſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151937:73"/>
                        <head>How we may be preſent with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion at Maſſe. <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IT is a thing both moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and profitable to heare maſſe euery day: ſynce the fruits that we reape thereby, be many and great; for as much as by that oblation the merits of our Sauiours paſſion be applied vnto vs.</p>
                        <p>Thereby alſo we receiue the remiſſion of our veniall ſyns, &amp; pardon of part of the paynes, that we haue deſerued for them.</p>
                        <p>We obtayne many graces &amp; fauours, and great ſtrength for the reſiſting of tentations, and good ſucceſſe in our affaires and actions, both ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151937:74"/> when it is expedient, and for our good. And more then this we are oftentymes preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daungers, and misſhaps, that might haue befallen vs, if we had not heard maſſe that day.</p>
                        <p>Wherefore for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe ſo excellent fruits, we muſt ſeeke to put theſe foure things in practiſe.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. We muſt exerciſe fayth, by conſidering that in Maſſe is repreſented, as in a Theater, the life &amp; paſſion of our Sauiour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing aſſuredly the ſame to be a true ſacrifice, wherein the body &amp; bloud of our Bleſſed Sauiour is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated, &amp; immolated to God the Father, &amp; that it is the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which Ieſus Chriſt made of himſelfe vpon the tree of the Croſſe: but yet with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that vpon the Croſſe it
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151937:74"/> was bloudy, &amp; in it own forme, and in maſſe it is vnbloudy, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kindes of bread and wyne.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt heare Maſſe with great reuerence and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both inward and outward, obſeruing what is ſaid and done both by the words and actions: for in maſſe be repreſented ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry myſteryes of our fayth.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt, together with the Prieſt, offer vnto God the holy ſacrifice of the maſſe for the very ſame intention which he offered it to the diuine maieſty. As namely, 1. For the due honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God. 2. For the rendring him thanks. 3. For the cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our ſyns. 4. For the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of graces &amp; benefits of God. And euery tyme that we preſent vnto him this oblation, we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151937:75"/> much, and it is of ſingular e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect. And we preſent him alſo with a thing, moſt acceptable to his diuine maieſty, for as much as he, who is offred and ſacrificed to God the Father, is the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne.</p>
                        <p>We muſt alſo communicate ſpiritually, at what tyme the prieſt receyueth ſacramentally. The manner to do it is this. We muſt meditate ſome thing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touching the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Altar, before the Prieſt be to communicate, and make petition to our Lord, that he would pleaſe to graunt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall refection vnto our ſoule, and to make it partaker of the wonderfull effects of this holy Sacrament. We muſt alſo put on a great deſire of vniting our
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151937:75"/> ſelues with God by that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all communion: and we muſt ſtir vp the very ſame affections, that we would do when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it ſacramentally, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="chapter">
                        <head>How to pray well. <hi>CHAP. V.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>TO pray well, and deuoutly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt practiſe ſomthings before we begin to pray &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things alſo in tyme of prayer.</p>
                        <p>Before we begin to pray, it is good firſt to bleſſe our ſelues: for by ſo doing we inuoke Gods help, we offer vnto him our prayers, we arme our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſtractions, and againſt the aſſaults of the enemy. 2. We are to conſider, for whome,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151937:76"/> and for what cauſe we haue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pray, which muſt be both good, and conforme to the will of God. 3. We muſt ſtir vp a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pray both attentiuely and deuoutly. 4. We muſt craue grace to pray well, and recommend our ſelues to our Angell Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
                        <p>Whiles our prayer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth we muſt endeauour to pray, 1. With a true fayth, belieuing in God that he will help vs, and that he heareth, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth our prayers.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. With hope, truſting that we ſhall be heard, if we pray as we ſhould.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. With charity, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the grace of God, or at leaſt with true ſorrow &amp; repentance for our ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. With humility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151937:76"/> as being in the preſence of God with whome we treate.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. With attention, bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing from our mynds all extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagant and wandring thoughts. And our attention may be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to one of theſe foure things: eyther to the words of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; or to the ſenſe and meaning ſignified by the words; or to him to whome we addreſſe our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or to the thing we craue for our ſelues, or for another.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. With feruour, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout affection, ſhaking off all drowſines of mind.</p>
                        <p>To this feruour and deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the conſideration of the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites that redound of prayer, being accompanyed with the qualityes aforeſaid, may incite vs. And there be foure principal that are drawn from ſuch pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151937:77"/> For by meanes of it we merit, 1. an increaſe of diuine graces, and vertues. 2. we ſatisfy, and pay a part of the debt we owe for our ſyns. 3 we obtayne of God that which we aſke. 4. we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue ſpirituall comfort.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="chapter">
                        <head>Remedyes againſt distractions. <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>BECAVSE diſtractions much trouble vs in tyme of prayer, and do very often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue vs of al the fruits aforeſaid, it is to good purpoſe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the remedyes for the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therof, and putting them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
                        <p>Therfore, that diſtraction may haue no place in vs, the firſt remedy is, that we diligently
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151937:77"/> prepare our ſelues to prayer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that we mentioned in the fift Chapter before.</p>
                        <p>The ſecond is, to thinke in whoſe preſence we are, and with whome we are to treate.</p>
                        <p>The third, to reſtrayne our ſight from looking one way or other: for the very leaſt obiect that we caſt our eyes on, doth forthwith giue vs matter and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſome diſtraction or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                        <p>For the putting away of the diſtraction that is once entred, and hath ſeized vpon our imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, we muſt ſerue our ſelues of theſe remedyes.</p>
                        <p>The firſt is, that ſo ſoone, as we mark our ſelues to be diſtracted, we put it away by thinking ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon God, or vpon the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnification of the words which
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151937:78"/> we vtter, or vpon the things we deſire to obtayne by our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                        <p>The ſecond, that we craue help of God, and of our guardian An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</p>
                        <p>The third, if the diſtraction hath been in ſome ſort voluntary we muſt craue humbly pardon of God, and purpoſe neuer more to admit any ſuch voluntary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction.</p>
                        <p>If diſtracting thoughts be importune without any of our fault, and that we connot eaſily driue them away; we muſt not be troubled therefore, ſith ſuch diſtraction is not ſyn (becauſe it hapneth vnto vs againſt our wil) but matter rather of meriting much before God, for that we haue by it an occaſion preſented vs, of humbling our ſelues, to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151937:78"/> conſider our weaknes and inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficiency, and matter alſo of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing our ſelues in patience.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="chapter">
                        <head>How to heare the word of God with profit. <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IT is expedient for a Chriſtian man to frequent the Sermons that are made, for the increaſe of his fayth, hope, and charity, and for the rooting out of vices, and planting of vertues in his ſoule. And therefore it is not inough to read good books, for that a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing voyce hath more force and efficacy, then hath the ſimple reading.</p>
                        <p>Wherfore if a man will make his profit by hearing the word of God preached, before the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151937:79"/> begin he muſt craue grace of God, that he may giue eare vnto it with profit.</p>
                        <p>In the Sermon tyme, he muſt giue eare firſt with a good and right intention, &amp; with a great deſire to reap fruit for his ſoules good, and not for curioſity, or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her vaine pleaſure; becauſe that were to profane an holy thing.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt receyue Gods word with great reuerence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God ſpeaketh vnto vs by the mouth of his ſeruants.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. With great attention, conſidering what moſt of al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth himſelfe, and toucheth him neereſt.</p>
                        <p>After the Sermon, he muſt firſt call to mind the principall points he hath heard, reflect v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, and conſider them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151937:79"/> well, and apply them vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt ſtir vp in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a deſire, and purpoſe to put the ſame in execution.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. When any occaſion ſhal preſent it ſelfe, he muſt put in practiſe the admonitions &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments, which he hath heard: For our Sauiour ſayth in <hi>S. Luke Cap.</hi> 11. <hi>That happy shall they be, who keep the word of God,</hi> and not thoſe who heare it only.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="chapter">
                        <head>How we muſt read Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Books. <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>BECAVSE the reading of good books is a ſoueraigne meanes for our progreſſe &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in the way of ſpirit, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151937:80"/> to know the manner how to read them with fruite. And therefore we muſt read them thus.</p>
                        <p>Firſt with a right intention, &amp; not for any curious, eloquent, or fluent diſcourſe: nor out of a deſire to know: nor only for the vnderſtanding of the propriety and nature of vertue, or of ſyn; but moſt of all for exciting vs to good life.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In reading, to ſtir vp our ſelues to the loue of God, to the purchaſing of vertue, to an hatred of ſyn, and eſchewing the ſame, and to conceyue a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and deſire to practiſe what we reade.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The better to excite our ſelues ſo to do, we muſt not read haſtly, nor runne lightly ouer, but leaſurely, and with great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151937:80"/> pawſing oftentymes for a ſpace, eſpecially when we read ſome good inſtruction: rumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that which God layeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes. <hi>For</hi> (as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſayth) <hi>by prayer we ſpeake to God, and by reading God ſpeaketh vnto vs.</hi> We muſt not trouble our ſelues, though by this occaſion we read not much, ſith better it is to read a little with great fruite, then much with little fruite. At the day of acompt, and of iudgment God will not regard the great number of ſpirituall books we ſhall haue turned ouer and read, but with what profit we ſhall haue read them.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To endeauour to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what we ſhall haue read. For to know good, and not to do it, is a ſyn, as <hi>S. Iames</hi> beareth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="138" facs="tcp:151937:81"/>
                        <head>The manner of examining our Conſcience. <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IT profiteth exceedingly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xamine the conſcience euery day at night, thereby to diſpoſe our ſelues to receyue pardon for our committed ſyns, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile our ſelues to God before our going to reſt. And this exame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comprehendeth fiue points.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To giue God thanks for his benefits, and in particular for this, that he hath not puniſhed vs forthwith after our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him, as he hath puniſhed many: but hath giuen vs tyme to do pennance for the ſame.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To demaund grace to examine our conſcience duely &amp;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151937:81"/> as we ought, and to acknowledg all our tranſgreſſions which we haue committed all that day, &amp; knowing them to deteſt them with a great &amp; inward feeling of mind, and ſorow.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To call to mind and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch out the ſyns which we haue that day committed by thought, word, work, and by omiſſion of that which we were bound to do. And for the wel making of this examination, it will be good to conſider, if we haue done any thing againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſeruice of God, againſt iuſtice, or charity due to our neighbour, or againſt Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, or the Churches, running ouer all the houres of the day, and the places where we haue been, by examining how we haue carried our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:151937:82"/> ſuch or ſuch a perſon, in ſuch and ſuch an affaire and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes, or how we haue diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſelues in our office.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To ſtir vp great ſorrow and compunction of hart, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing offended the diuine maieſty ſo often: and that done to make a firme purpoſe of amendment, not to fall any more into ſyn, &amp; to ſhun the occaſions that be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements of falling thereinto: and further to make a purpoſe to go to Confeſſion.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. With an harty affection and feruour of ſpirit to craue of God, that by his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; by the paſſion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, he would pleaſe to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell our ſyns: &amp; then to demaund grace of amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the tyme to come.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="141" facs="tcp:151937:82"/>
                        <head>How to make a good Confeſſion. <hi>CHAP. X.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>FOR as much, as for obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning abſolution from our ſyns, it is not inough to make any manner of confeſſion, but it is expedient to know, what we are to do before confeſſion; what to do in Confeſſion; and what againe after the ſame.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Before Confeſſion in the firſt place we muſt diligently examin our conſcience, after the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner before declared, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring &amp; calling of our ſyns to mind, when we are to go to confeſſion.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Hauing laid before the eyes of our mind, the ſyns we haue committed ſince our laſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151937:83"/> confeſſion, we muſt ſtir vp a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne diſpleaſure againſt our ſelues, and ſorow for hauing ſo much offended the diuine maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as we haue declared in the ſecond Chapter.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt conceyue a firme purpoſe of amendment for the tyme to come, and of falling no more into ſyn, and of ſhuning the occaſions, and dangers of ſyn.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He that after examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his conſcience, forgetteth in confeſſion any mortall ſyn: or he, who is not ſufficiently peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for his faults, or hath not a true deſire to lyue better, &amp; to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from the vice or ſyn wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he findeth himſelfe incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is not wel diſpoſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue abſolution of his ſyns and therfore the next tyme he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151937:83"/> to confeſſion, he muſt rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate ſuch a confeſſion, that was defectiue in one of the three things aforeſaid; and moreouer, declare and manifeſt to his gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly Father that, wherein he was faulty in his former confeſſion; becauſe ſuch a willfull fault is a mortall ſyn.</p>
                        <p>Hauing made choice of a vertuous, prudent &amp; expert gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly Father, he muſt come vnto him with a right intention; that is, to be abſolued from his ſyns, and with a deſire to manifeſt his whole conſcience vnto him. And further with great reuerence &amp; humility, conſidering that, as a malefactour, he preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his Iudge, and to him, who is our Lords Vicar on earth. And aboue all, he muſt come with great contrition: for
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:151937:84"/> if he go only, becauſe it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or of cuſtome, he ſhall ſtill continue in the ſame imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in great daunger to be abandoned and forſaken of God.</p>
                        <p>During his confeſſion being vpon his knees, it is very good before he begin, to make the ſigne of the Croſſe, crauing help of God to make a good confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and then to aske the Prieſts benediction, ſaying; <hi>Benedic Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> and then to ſay the <hi>Confiteor</hi> vntil he come to <hi>mea culpa.</hi> It wil be good alſo in the beginning to declare the tyme, when he was laſt at confeſſion, and if he hath forgotten or concealed any ſyn in the confeſſion he made before, and if he neglected to do the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, enioyned him by his ghoſtly Father; and then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute his confeſſion, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151937:84"/> himſelfe of his ſyns.</p>
                        <p>To make this confeſſion good and auaylable, three things muſt concurre, to wit, Integrity, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and Obedience. I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them. To make an entiere confeſſion, a man muſt firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt al his ſyns, committed ſince his laſt confeſſion, lawfully made, without concealing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly any mortall ſyn, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he is aſſured it is ſuch, but alſo when he doubteth of it.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt declare them in particuler, and euery one in it own kind: in ſo much as it ſhoud not be inough for him to ſay, I haue been luxurious, I haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en iniury to my neighbour &amp;c. but that he muſt ſpecify euery particuler &amp; euery circumſtance, belonging therto.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <pb n="146" facs="tcp:151937:85"/>3. He muſt declare how often he hath committed euery mortall ſyn, as neere as he may gheſſe. If he cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ell the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine number, or neere vnto it, he muſt tell how long tyme he hath perſeuered in ſuch a ſyn.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He muſt alſo ſpecify all other neceſſary circumſtances, to the end the quality of euery ſyn may be throughly known to his ghoſtly Father. For he, that by occaſion of any confuſion &amp; ſhame or ſuch like reſpect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not an entiere confeſſion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner declared, is not abſolued before God: and more then that, he committeth a mortall ſyn, which is called the ſyn of ſacrilege, becauſe he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth a great irreuerence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sacrament, inſtituted by our Sauiour; in ſo much as
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151937:85"/> he is bound to reiterate ſuch a confeſſion, and to make a repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the ſame mortall ſyns that he then confeſſed; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to declare in particular the ſyn of ſacriledge, that he former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed therein.</p>
                        <p>To confeſſe faythfully and ſincerely, he muſt firſt manifeſt his ſyns without diſſimulation, or hypocriſy, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hout lying, without making them greater then they be, or extenuating, &amp; making them leſſe then they be, and without excuſing his ſyn contrary to the truth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out colouring it by fayre lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or obſcure words.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt take heede he confeſſe not his ſyns conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſaying, <hi>If I haue ſtolne &amp;c. I aske pardon:</hi> for ſuch a confeſſion auayleth nothing: but he muſt
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151937:86"/> confeſſe abſolutely, vnles it be doubtful, whether he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch a ſyn: for he muſt confeſſe that, which is certaine, as certaine and that which is doubtfull, as doubtfull.</p>
                        <p>That the confeſſion may be Obedient, the penitent muſt be ready to do all that, which his Ghoſtly Father ſhall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de him with reaſon, touching the good of his ſoule, in ſo much as he ought to be ready,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To accompliſh and do the pennance enioyned him for his ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To reſtore the goods of another, which he hath gotten vniuſtly, or the good name of his neighbour, which he hath ſpoyled him of, and taken from him by detraction, as his Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly Father ſhall eyther aduiſe, or
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151937:86"/> direct him. For the ſyn is not pardoned, if what hath beene taken away, be not reſtored, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayth.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To ſatisfy and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe domage and hurt, that he hath done to any one.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To reconcile himſelfe to his enemy, whome he hath wronged, and from his hart to pardon and forgiue him, who hath done him any iniury.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. To forbeare and ſhunne all occaſions and dangers of ſyn for the time to come.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. To practiſe the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes againſt ſyn in manner as he ſhall be aduiſed to do.</p>
                        <p>After confeſſion of his ſyns, for concluſion it will be good to adioyne theſe words: <hi>For all theſe my ſyns, and others, that I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which I now remember not, I
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151937:87"/> humbly craue pardon, penance and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution &amp;c. Ideo precor &amp;c.</hi> This done, he muſt giue attentiue eare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he good leſſon, and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Ghoſtly Father ſhall giue him, with an intention and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make vſe thereof.</p>
                        <p>After Confeſſion and Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, the penitent muſt go aſide, &amp; 1. Giue Gods thanks, for that it hath pleaſed his diuine Maieſty to pardon him all his ſyns, by mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of Sacramentall abſolution; and further to tender him thanks for all the good, that he hath gotten by the remiſſion of his ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. With deuotion to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the pennance, that his Ghoſtly Father enioyned him, without differing of it, if he may then do it.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To renew the good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151937:87"/> that he had made before, and to aske grace of God for wel doing therof.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="chapter">
                        <head>The cauſes, that ought to induce vs to true repentance for our ſyns. <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>FOR that without repentance for our ſyns it is impoſſible to receaue pardon for them; it is expedient to know the principal motyues, that ought to induce vs, and to ſtir vp a perfect ſorrow &amp; compunction for our ſyns, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the ſame be mortall. And to this purpoſe it will be good to conſider.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That by them we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of many ſoueraign goods, as of the grace of God, which far
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151937:88"/> ſurpaſſeth all the treaſures and goods of this world. Againe by them we are depriued of many ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tues, and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, without which we are, and remayne, as did <hi>Sampſon,</hi> in the hands of the <hi>Philiſtians,</hi> when he had loſt his ſtrength. We are further ſpoyled of all the meritts, which we had formerly gotten by our good works, and of the fruit of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we do in ſtate ſyn. Finally, we are made inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and vnworthy of eternall felicity, hauing loſt all the right, that we had thereunto.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To conſider, that we haue incurred many euills: for by ſyn we are become the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of God, yea the ſlaues, and very receptacle of the Diuell: and to be ſhort, we merit euerlaſting damnation.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <pb n="153" facs="tcp:151937:88"/>3. The chiefeſt motiue, that ought to induce vs to great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for our ſyns, is, for that we haue offended the diuine maieſty by our diſobedience, ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and contempt of him, and for that by our ſyn, we haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly iniured him, by louing ſome tranſitory good, and ſome pleaſure of the body, or ſome creature more then our Creatour and ſoueraigne Lord, and by preferring our owne will, and bad deſire, before the will and pleaſure of God, therein imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Iewes, who preferred <hi>Barabbas</hi> before our Sauiour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="154" facs="tcp:151937:89"/>
                        <head>The cauſes, for which it is very good, and moſt expedient to go often to Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>HE that loueth his owne ſoule, expecteth not the tyme of commaundment, or the abſolute neceſſity of going to confeſſion; but he confeſſeth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when there is not any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment impoſed vpon him, that he may gaine and reape the moſt excellent fruits, that be gathered in frequenting this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament.</p>
                        <p>For in often confeſſing, a man, 1. purchaſeth a great peace, repoſe and quiet of conſcience.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He euery tyme obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151937:89"/> great prouiſion, ſtore, and increaſe of vertues.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The good works, that were mortified, and made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable by mortall ſyn, returne to their worth, and become meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious againe.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He is made participant of all our Sauiours meritts, and of all the good works of the iuſt, and faythfull Chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was depriued, by mortall ſyn.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Euery tyme that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, he rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iueth great force and ſtrength for the reſiſting and encountring of his enemyes, and againſt all their tentations.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. He ſatisfieth a part of the payne, which after remiſſion of the fault remayneth behind, due to be payed, eyther in this world, or in Purgatory.</p>
                        <pb n="156" facs="tcp:151937:90"/>
                        <p>And what wiſe man, who conſidereth all theſe priuiledges, that ariſe of frequent Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wil not be greatly incited to go often therunto, for the often gayning and reaping of ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fruits? If a man were ſicke in body, if he had receyued any mortall and deadly wound, would he expect any long tyme to thinke vpon the curing of himſelfe? Or would he not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all poſſible ſpeed ſeek a Phiſitian, or Surgeon for his cure, for feare of a temporall death? And his ſoule beeing ſick, and daungerouſly wounded by ſyn; ſhould he ſo far neglect his ſaluation, as to put it of from day to day, from weeke to weeke, from moneth to moneth, from quarter to quarter &amp;c. and ſo hazard to incurre death for all
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151937:90"/> eternity?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="chapter">
                        <head>Of the great neceſſity, and vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Generall Confeſſion. <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>I call it a Generall Confeſſion, when a man confeſſeth all his ſyns, eſpecially the mortall, that he hath committed in all his life, or thoſe of a long tyme before, as far as he can remember, and call to mind, whether he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed them before, or not. This manner of Confeſſion is very profitable, and ſometymes alſo altogether neceſſary in matter of mortall ſyn, when in confeſſion ſome condition or other nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary is wanting, eyther on the part of the Confeſſour, or on the part of the penitent. And this
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151937:91"/> may happen in diuerſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. When one hath made his confeſſion to a prieſt, that had not lawfull auctority to abſolue, or for that he was not approued of the Biſhop, or for ſome other cauſe.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. When one hath confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed without being penitent and ſorowfull for his ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. When he had not a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of amendment, and abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from ſome ſynne: or when he wanted a will to forgiue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other who had offended him, or of reſtoring that to which he was bound.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. When ſome confeſſion made before was not entiere, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for wittingly, vpon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain baſhfulnes, concealing ſome mortall ſyn, or for ſome other
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151937:91"/> vnlawfull cauſe; or for hauing forgotten to confeſſe ſome mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſyn, becauſe he had not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined his conſcience before.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. When before abſolution he had a wil not to accept of it, or not to fulfill the pennance, enioyned him by his ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                        <p>Lo the principall cauſes, for which it often hapneth, that a generall Confeſſion is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for that the Confeſſion made before with any one of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid defects was not ſufficient to obtayn the remiſſion of our ſyns. And all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſions made after that, were vnprofitable; in ſo much as it behooueth him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to confeſſe all the mortall ſyns, that he had manifeſted in that Confeſſion, and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that followed; and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151937:92"/> the cauſe and the fault for which he maketh a Generall Confeſſion.</p>
                        <p>And though a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion be not to ſome neceſſary, becauſe they neuer made default in making their Confeſſion; yet it much profiteth them for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reaſons.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. For by confeſſing al their ſyns together of many moneths, or yeares, a man conceyueth greater ſorrow for his ſyns, and confuſion of himſelfe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he obtayneth greater grace, and ſatisfieth more of the payne, due to his ſyns.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He is much incited to the loue of God, in conſidering his great benignity and mercy, by which he hath ſupported and borne with him ſo patiently, without puniſhing him for ſo
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:151937:92"/> many ſyns committed by him.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. By conſidering the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his ſyns heaped and put together, he is moued to do good works for the ſatisfying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He obtayneth greater aſſurance, and repoſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſpirituall ioy: for he, who hath made a generall confeſſion, may probably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe, that his ſoule is in good eſtate.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="chapter">
                        <head>How to communicate with fruit. <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>HE, that deſireth to receyue the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Altar with fruite, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall profit, muſt haue.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. A firme fayth, belieuing
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151937:93"/> vndoubtedly, that Ieſus Chriſt is really, and truly in the holy Sacrament, and that in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion he receyueth the true body of our Sauiour, who is true man, the ſame, who was borne of the moſt ſacred Virgin Mary, who endured death for vs, and is one day to iudge both the lyuing and the dead.</p>
                        <p n="2">2: He muſt haue Purity of hart, without hauing his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience defiled with any mortall ſyn, that maketh a man vtterly vnworthy of the participation of this Sacrament: and alſo in preſuming to come thereunto in ſuch bad ſtate, he ſhould commit a ſyn of ſacriledge.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. He muſt haue a right intention, intending to receyue the Sacrament for the attayning of increaſe of Gods grace; to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151937:93"/> obtaine ſome particular vertue, whereof he moſt ſtandeth in neede; to arme and ſtrengthen himſelfe the more againſt the tentations of his enemyes; to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite himſelfe more inwardly with God by that band of loue: For the receyuing of this Bleſſed Sacrament ſerueth vs for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of all theſe heauenly graces, and many more the like.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He muſt receyue with great deuotion. And that he may ſo do, he muſt endeauour to come to the Sacrament. 1. With great humility &amp; reuerence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his owne vnworthines miſery, and neceſſity, and the ſupreme Maieſty of him, whome he is to receyue into his ſoule.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To conſider the cauſes,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151937:94"/> for which this holy Sacrament was inſtituted, and the great charity of our Sauiour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he vouchſafed to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelfe to his creatures, and to giue himſelfe in foode &amp; nutryment to our ſoules. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo the great fruits, that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> receyued in this holy banquet: becauſe this ſpirituall food pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the ſame effects in our ſoule, that doth materiall meate in our bodyes, though after a manner much more excellent.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To communicate with a ſpirituall hunger, and feruent deſire to feede, and fill his ſoule with this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly meate, &amp; with prayers and petitions full of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffection, and of loue, to craue grace of God to communicate deuoutely, and to receyue all the fruits of this holeſome refection.</p>
                        <pb n="165" facs="tcp:151937:94"/>
                        <p>After receyuing, he muſt giue thanks to God for pleaſing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the chamber of his ſoule: there to make his aboade, and to fill it with his grace, and gifts of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He muſt offer himſelfe wholy to his Creatour, who hath giuen, and communicated himſelfe ſo liberally vnto his Creatour.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. By ſhort, and as it were inculatory prayers, he muſt treate familiarly with his Spouſe, &amp; repreſent vnto him his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, and neceſſityes, crauing what he ſtandeth moſt in need of, &amp; beſeeching him to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to make his continuall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad with him, &amp; to keep him in his grace.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="166" facs="tcp:151937:95"/>
                        <head>The cauſes, that ought to induce vs to the frequent receyuing of this Sacrament. <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IF materiall meate be often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes neceſſary for our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation and nuriture of body; we muſt not make any doubt, but that the ſpirituall foode, which is the ſacred fleſh of our Sauiour, contayned in the holy ſacrament of the Euchariſt, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo often as neceſſary for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayning and nouriſhing of our ſoule. And if we regard not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the neceſſity, but the good al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which our ſoule receyueth by this heauenly food, it is a thing truly very great; for as much as
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151937:95"/> by the often receyuing of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine meate:</p>
                        <p>Firſt our ſoule is eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and intertayned in Gods grace, for that beeing often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with this food, grace is increaſed more and more in it.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Euery tyme of receyuing, it getteth wonderfull ſtrength for the exerciſing of good works, for the reſiſting of the tentations of our enemyes, for preſeruing it from ſyn; and for patiently ſupporting and bearing al aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſityes of this preſent life.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. This food cauſeth a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table chaung of life in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that was before ſubiect to many vices and imperfections.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. It augmenteth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in vs fayth, hope, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deuotion, &amp; al other vertues.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <pb n="168" facs="tcp:151937:96"/>5. It filleth and repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the ſoule with a ſpirituall ioy, and alacrity.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. It raceth out of our ſoule veniall ſyns, and weakneth and leſſeneth vicious inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; concupiſcence.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. It vniteth our ſoule with Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>For he, who ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my flesh</hi> (ſayth our Sauiour in <hi>S. Iohn Cap.</hi> 6. (<hi>abideth in me, and I in him.</hi> If we with attention would ponder, and conſider all theſe ſo ſoueraigne fruits, we ſhould be much excited very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to refreſh our ſoule with this ſo healthfull a meat.</p>
                        <p>If we giue euery day to our body to eate, nouriſhing, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning and ſtrengthning ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; is it not reaſon, that our ſoule, that hath alſo exceeding great need of nuriture and new
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151937:96"/> ſtrength, ſhould be entertayned with this heauenly food, at leaſt once a moneth?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="chapter">
                        <head>Remedyes for the auoyding of ſyns, and reſisting of tentations. <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>MANY there be, who find in themſelues a deſire to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their lyfe, and purpoſe no more to fall againe into ſyn, which is ſo diſpleaſing vnto God, and ſo preiudiciall to their ſoules: but they are not able to reſiſt the tentations, that aſſayle them; in ſo much as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their good deſire, and good purpoſe, they fall againe and againe into their ſyns. The
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151937:97"/> principall cauſe whereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth of this, for that they ſerue not themſelues of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, that be proper and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for the reſiſting of tentation and ſyn: and therefore I will here lay downe ſome few reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, wherewith we may ſerue our turne at all tymes, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we find our ſelues inclined to ſyn.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To conſider the great priuiledges, whereof ſyn ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, and the great euills and hurts it cauſeth vnto vs, which you ſhall find declared in the <hi>XI. Chapter</hi> before.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To conſider, that we are contynually in the preſence of God: that in all places, and at all tymes he ſeeth, knoweth, &amp; obſerueth our thoughts, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, all which he will in the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151937:97"/> day of iudgment lay open, and manifeſt to the whole world, &amp; will giue ſentence againſt vs by them. And if you would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print well this conſideration in your mynd, and apprehend it, as you ought, it will ſerue you for a ſpur to incite, and to put you forward to vertue; and for a bridle to pull in, and repreſſe your diſordered appeties. For how wil you be ſo hardy to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that before God, that you would not dare to do before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To conſider, that by reſiſting ſyn, and tentation, we receyue a great increaſe of grace, and a great ioy, &amp; ſpirituall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation therewith.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To make a firme pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to offend God, and in particular not to commit ſuch, or ſuch a ſyn: and very
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151937:98"/> often to renew the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. To bleſſe your ſelfe with the ſigne of the Croſſe, and to craue help from God, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Saints.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. To reſiſt the beginnings of bad thoughts, and to repreſſe our paſſions and inordinate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffections at the very firſt.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. To auoyd and fly the occaſions, that may make vs to fall into any ſyn, as ydlenes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much talke, curioſity to ſee, and heare any thing that profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not. Alſo to fly the places, where God is eaſily offended, the conuerſation and company of diſordred perſons, &amp; ouer much familiarity with any perſon. For he, who will not fly ſuch like occaſions, expoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to an euident daunger of falling into ſome ſyn, or other.
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151937:98"/> 
                           <hi>And he</hi> (ſayth the <hi>VViſeman Eccl.</hi> 3.) <hi>who loueth daunger, shall pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ish in it.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. To frequent the holy Sacraments of Confeſſion, &amp; the Euchariſt.</p>
                        <p n="9">9. To exerciſe acts of vertue, contrary to the vices, whereunto we are tempted, or moſt inclined: as if we be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to gluttony, to mortify our ſenſuality, &amp; vſe abſtinence: if we be ſollicited to pride &amp; vaine glory, to exerciſe ſome act of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, inward or outward, by conſideration of our owne frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; miſery: &amp; ſo other vertues.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="chapter">
                        <head>The manner, how to poſſeſſe our ſelues of ſome ſolid Vertue. <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>FOR the more eaſy obtayning the habit and vſe of vertues,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:151937:99"/> we muſt make election but of one at once, as of Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Patience, or ſome other, that we thinke moſt neceſſary for vs, and therein imploy all our chiefeſt ſtudy and care for the getting therof: and after ſome tyme take an other Vertue, and ſo conſequently the reſt. The meanes to get it, is this.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To aske it of God ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſantly, by feruent and deuout prayers.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To put on a great and earneſt deſire to get it. And this deſire is increaſed very much by meditating and pondering the beauty, and excellency of the vertue, how pleaſing it is to God, and how neceſſary and profitable for vs.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To lay before our eyes the examples of the Saints and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151937:99"/> holy men, in whome ſuch a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath ſhined, eſpecially the example of our Sauiour, and of our Bleſſed Lady.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To practiſe it often and to exerciſe our ſelues in it by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions, proceeding from ſuch a vertue.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. To auoyd the very leaſt faults, that haue repugnance with that vertue, and in general all veniall ſyns, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder our profit in vertue.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. Euery day to make a particular examen, how we haue carryed our ſelues in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerciſe of ſuch a vertue, and wherein we haue fayled.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="exercise">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151937:100"/>
                     <head>The ſecond Part, of the Way to lyue well. THE VIII. EXERCISE.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>What we are to do in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of God. <hi>CHAP. I.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IN diſcharge of our duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Gods, we muſt, Firſt loue him aboue all things, and not for any other end then for himſelfe, and this for that he is Goodnes it ſelfe, and the only authour, ſource and beginning of all good. And we may know, whether we haue the loue of God, if we be ready rather to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandone all the goods of this
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:151937:100"/> world, yea and our owne life al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, then to offend him mortally in any thing.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt haue a great deſire and zeale to promote and aduaunce his honour, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt haue a right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in all things, &amp; addreſſe all our actions to his greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, without intermixing any leſſe-rectified, or vicious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. We muſt endeauour &amp; ſeeke to pleaſe him in all things, and fly all that, which we know to be diſpleaſing vnto him.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. We muſt faſten the anker of our hope wholy in him, and in all our neceſſityes make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to him for help and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. We muſt daily giue him
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:151937:101"/> thanks for the benefitts, he hath beſtowed and continually doth beſtow vpon vs.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. We muſt oftentymes treat familiarly with him, by thought, and eleuation of mind, and by iaculatory prayers, that is, by ſhort, ſodaine &amp; effectuous petitions, which may be done in all places, and at all tymes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <head>What we are to do in behalfe of the Saints: and namely of the Bleſſed Virgin. <hi>CHAP. II.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IF we deſire to be pleaſing to God, we muſt be deuout to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Saints, who are his great friends, and eſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Bleſſed Virgin, his glorious Mother. To do this we
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:151937:101"/> muſt firſt loue and honour her, as moſt worthy of our loue, and of all regard and reuerence; becauſe ſhe is our heauenly mother, full of mercy, and loue, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all manner of grace, and ſhineth with rare ſanctity, and incomparable vertue.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt dayly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our ſelues vnto her, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreating her interceſſion for vs, and her protection of vs: wherein ſhe may much ſteed vs, and eaſily obtayne that, which we deſerue not to obtayne by our ſelues: becauſe ſhe is a moſt holy Virgin, and moſt accepted to God, and is the mother of our Lord, and Queene of heauen.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt often contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate this beautyfull mirrour, &amp; Looking-glaſſe, without any ſtayne of ſyn, ſhining in all
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:151937:102"/> manner of vertues: and we muſt endeuour to order our lyfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to hers, and imitate her holy and vertuous actions: and ſo doing we ſhall do her ſeruice, that pleaſeth and contenteth her moſt of all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <head>How we are to cary our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our good Angell. <hi>CHAP. III.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>BECAVSE God (by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>S. Hierome</hi> and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Fathers) ſendeth vs our good Angell preſently after our comming into the world, to aſſiſt, and attend, ſerue, protect conduct, and direct vs in all our actions, reaſon teacheth, that we ought, Firſt to cary a ſingular loue towards him, as to a moſt
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151937:102"/> particular benefactour of ours. For we are more bound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o him, then to any other, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xt after God, and our Bleſſed Lady.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt thanke him hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and affectuouſly for all the good offices, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e dayly doth vs.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We muſt make our often recourſe vnto him, by crauing his help in all occurrents, and affaires of ours; for he is deputed of God to that end, and moſt ready to aſſiſt vs, out of the zeale and deſire he hath of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. We muſt giue eare to his good counſayles, motions, and inſpirations, that he putteth into our minds.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. We muſt dayly conſider, that we are continually in the preſence of our good Angell and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:151937:103"/> that euery where he conſidereth, &amp; obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>eth our comportment, demeanour, and cariage. And this conſideration will ſerue vs for a bridle againſt ſyn.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="chapter">
                        <head>What our Good Angell doth towards vs. <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THE office of our Guardian Angell towards euery one of vs, is; firſt to make inceſſant prayer, and petition for vs, and to preſent vnto God our prayers, and good works.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. To excite and ſtir vs vp to lyue well, and to withdraw and diuert vs fron doing euill.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. To preſerue and keep our bodyes from manyfold ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe accidents and daungers,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:151937:103"/> that might very often befall vs, if we were not in his pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ection and ſafegard.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. To guard and defend our ſoule againſt all treacheries, and tentations of the malignant ſpirit. For (if we belieue <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nyſſen, Tertullian, Caſſian, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Bede,</hi> and other ancyent Fathers) we haue euer about vs two ſpirits, one whereof is our good Angell, who wholy atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth our ſoules good; the other a Diuell, deputed and appointed by his Prince <hi>Lucifer,</hi> to imploy and buſy himſelfe wholy for the ſolliciting, and tempting of vs to ſyn, thereby to procure our vtter perdition, &amp; eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="184" facs="tcp:151937:104"/>
                        <head>How we ought to carry our ſelues towards our ſelues. <hi>CHAP. V.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>EVERY one of vs ought to keepe an euen hand ouer himſelfe in gouerning his body, in eating and drinking, in repoſe and in ſleepe, in his demeanour and carriage, in his functions, offices, trauayles: and eſpecially he muſt haue a moſt ſingular care of his ſoule, becauſe it is the excellenteſt, and nobleſt part of man, and therfore of the felicity or infelicity of it dependeth the good or euill of the body for all Eternity.</p>
                        <p>Wherfore to tender our ſoule, as we ought, we muſt; firſt deſire, procure, &amp; practiſe with al dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:151937:104"/> &amp; care, what may be moſt for the profiting &amp; ſauing therof.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt carefully deteſt, &amp; fly what is domageable vnto it, ſuch as is ſyn, and all occaſion, and daunger of offending God.</p>
                        <p n="3">3; We muſt bridle and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne our ouer much liberty of ſpeaking, and ſaying, what is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> conuenient: as alſo our ouer much curioſity to ſee, heare, and vnderſtand that, which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs not at al. For this liberty and curioſity otherwhiles mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth vnto vs matter of ſynning.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. We muſt mortify, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome our paſſions, vicious motions of choller, impatience, and pride, and all our inordinate appetites of eating and drinking, and of ſeeking our commodities, eaſe, and pleaſure.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. We muſt manfully reſiſt
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:151937:105"/> our bad cuſtomes, and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and withſtand the vices, whereunto we are ſubiect, and not permit, that we be ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any tentation, eyther of the world, fleſh, or Diuell.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="chapter">
                        <head>How we must carry our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbour. <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>TOVVARDS our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour we muſt exerciſe two vertues moſt of all, namely Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Charity. Iuſtice is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed firſt in keeping the right that is due vnto him, and doing that to him, whereunto we are obliged and bound, &amp; rendring vnto him what is his.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In doing him no wrong, nor hurt.</p>
                        <p>We muſt exerciſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards our neighbour, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:151937:105"/> him with hart, word, and worke. We loue him in har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, firſt being affectioned towards him, without rancour of mind, and diſcontent. And this alſo we muſt do towards them, who ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any enmity towards vs; &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, who haue wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs, becauſe it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Wiſhing and deſiring him all good as to our ſelues: &amp; not wiſhing him any harme, as we would not to our ſelues.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Beeing glad of his good, &amp; ſory for his hurt, as for our own.</p>
                        <p>We loue him in word: Firſt in ſpeaking well of him.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In taking heed we mock him not, nor contriſtate him, nor ſay any euill of him, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne him eyther in preſence, which is contumely; nor in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:151937:106"/> which is detraction.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. In beeing affable &amp; cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in conuerſation with him, without vſing any rough, or harſh words, or ſpeaches vnto him.</p>
                        <p>We loue him by worke, and really. Firſt in helping him in that, wherein he ſtandeth in neede of vs, eyther by almes, or any other worke of Charity, and mercy, eyther corporall or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; as by good inſtructions, counſayle, admonition, comfort, prayers: and finally in doing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him all that, which we would haue done to vs: for we ought to loue him, as we loue our ſelues.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In taking carefull heed we ſcandalize him not, nor giue him any bad example, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king rather to edify him by our good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>portment &amp; behauiour.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <pb n="189" facs="tcp:151937:106"/>3. In ſupporting his faults and infirmityes.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. In bearing patiently what he hath ſaid, or done to vs.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. In truly pardoning him that hath offended vs, as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that God would pardon vs, when we haue offended him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="chapter">
                        <head>How we must carry our ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Superiors. <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>CHILDREN towards their parents, ſeruants of both ſexes towards their maiſters, &amp; miſtreſſes, the Religious, and al ſubiects towards their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, ought to cary themſelues in an other manner, then towards others, who haue not any ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority ouer them.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="190" facs="tcp:151937:107"/>1. We owe vnto them a ſingular loue &amp; affection, which conſiſteth in wiſhing &amp; deſiring them good, and in endeuouring to content and pleaſe them in al, that ſtandeth with reaſon, and hath relation to God: and in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diligent heed not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſtate, or diſpleaſe them, or to do that which may diſpleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. We muſt reſpect and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them with an inward and outward reuerence, becauſe they hold Gods place, &amp; repreſent our Lords perſon. We muſt alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware we giue them not any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuil, contemptuous, or arrogant anſweres: we muſt not mock or blame them, nor complain of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to others. If any ſpeak euil of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt ſeeke to excuſe them, &amp; maintaine their honour &amp; good name.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <pb n="191" facs="tcp:151937:107"/>3. We muſt obey what they commaund; &amp; therin three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions are requiſite for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of true obedience, which conſiſt in the Execution, in the Will, and in the Vnderſtanding.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. As touching the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt obey with promptitude and readynes, without delay, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierly, and not by peece-meales.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Concerning the Will, we muſt obey them willingly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contrariety, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content or murmuring, without giuing of any ſigne of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without allegatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vayne excuſes, but merily and cheere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully without ſadnes, or diſguſt, ſincerely and not to the eye, not with fraud &amp; malice, manfully and couragiouſly, not doing o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly willingly what is eaſy to do, &amp; pleaſing vnto vs; but alſo that,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:151937:108"/> which is hard, paynefull, &amp; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant to ſenſuality and ſelf loue.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Touching the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we muſt obey ſimply, and humbly ſubiecting &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forming our Iudgment to that of our Superiours, without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting in our hart what they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, as though it were not reaſonable, or lawful to be done.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. We muſt giue then attentiue hearing, and with al humility &amp; alacrity of hart receyue their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, admonitions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, as though they came immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God: &amp; we muſt giue teſtimony by ſignes and words, that we are pleaſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: and we muſt endeuour to make our profit of all.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Finally we muſt help &amp; aſſiſt them in their neceſſiryes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151937:108"/>
                  <p>PIOVS MEDITATIONS VPON THE BEADES:</p>
                  <p>For deteſtation of Synne; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of Chriſtian Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and dayly Memory of the Life, and Paſſion of Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
                  <p>Tranſlated out of Spaniſh.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal of Society of Jesus</figDesc>
                     <p>IHS</p>
                  </figure>
                  <p>M.DC.XX.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151937:109"/>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:151937:109"/>
                  <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Deuout Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Catholique Church, for the profit of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their firſt conuerſion, and afterwards as occaſions require, maketh vſe of the laudable cuſtomes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, adioyning to them pious conſiderations and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerciſes, to aduaunce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:151937:110"/> deuotion. And becauſe the vſe of the Beades is both eaſy and profitable, and for this reſpect receyued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in all Countries: in tymes paſt there were added to the <hi>Roſary</hi> of our Bleſſed Lady diuers Meditations and Contemplations. And heere (gentle Reader) thou ſhalt ſee adioyned to her Crowne or <hi>Coronary,</hi> others, for the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>Mortall ſynne</hi> aboue all thinges to be deteſted; for the obtayning of <hi>Christian Perfection,</hi> which is the ſcope of all our actions; and finally of the <hi>principall Myſteries</hi> of the Life &amp; Paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, which we ſhould
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:151937:110"/> keepe in perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, both to imitate his vertues, and to be thankefull for his benefits.</p>
                  <p>For ſeeing we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothing els for him, that hath done ſo much for vs: at leaſt, our care &amp; deuotion ſhould call once a day to memory, how much we are owing to his loue: and neuer be weary to thinke of thoſe afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; torments, which he was not weary to ſuffer for our ſakes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe variety in all exerciſes is a remedy againſt wearineſſe, and eſpecially in matters of deuotion; we haue done heere as in Muſike is both permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and commended, where
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:151937:111"/> many tymes they ſing diuers ditties vnder one tune, when it is good.</p>
                  <p>It wilbe eaſy for thee to accomodate theſe particuler conſiderations to the number of the Beades, beginning with the firſt three, &amp; ending with the ſame; and intermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xing the <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and Prayers according to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers heere ſet downe. And at the firſt it will greatly helpe thy memory, to haue the Booke before thee, and reade the points one by one, as thou ſayeſt the Prayers; till with cuſtome thou ſhalt haue gotten them without booke. And whileſt thou ſayeſt the
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:151937:111"/> 
                     <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> thou muſt haue reflexion to the point which thou haſt read: &amp; ſo go from one to another, with leaſure and attention, till thou haue paſſed them all ouer: and doubt not, but with a little patience for the firſt few dayes, thou ſhalt reape after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a great deale of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, deuotion, and benefit to thy ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Conſiderations or points of Meditation, were conceaued, and wrytten in Spaniſh in the yeare 1613. for intertaynment of the way between <hi>Madrid</hi> and <hi>Barcelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and there printed: &amp; from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſent to <hi>Don Philip</hi> Prince
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:151937:112"/> of Spaine, and to his two brethren <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; <hi>Ferdinand</hi> for tokens, in reſpect that the Author, when be tooke his laſt leaue, left them ſaying their beads al three togeather: and comming after by ſome accident into England, and there tranſlated by a deuout perſon, were ſent to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and by chance brought to be viewed, before the printing, by the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that wrote them in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſix yeares before; he little thinking then, that they were to be publiſhed in any other language, which he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for priuate deuotion of thoſe Princes. But by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:151937:112"/> it ſeemeth that God, of his holy prouidence, would haue ſome thing written for the inſtruction of ſuch, as ſhal read the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where the vſe of the Beades is not knowen to all. And in this conformity he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe few lines, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that deuotion be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the faithfull people, and God Almighty glorified, from whome all Grace &amp; goodnes deſcendeth, and to whome is due all honour and glory. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:151937:113"/>
                  <head>A Coronary or Crowne of <hi>63. Aue Maries:</hi> with a Prayer to the euer bleſſed Virgin Mary, that by her Interceſsion we may liue &amp; dye without mortall ſin.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Syn is an inordinate, and deliberate worke, word, or deſire, againſt the eternall law of God. <bibl>
                           <hi>S. Auguſt. lib.</hi> 22. <hi>contra Fauſtum.</hi> cap. 27.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer to the B. Virgin.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. O Mary Mother of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and example of inocency, who dideſt ſee thy on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne dye moſt lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vpon the croſſe, to deliuer vs
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:151937:113"/> from the bondage of ſyn; obtayn for me, bleſſed Virgin, light to know, and hatred to abhor ſo great a miſchiefe, as thou thy ſelf dideſt knowe it, and abhor it. Amen. <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. That I may <hi>vnderſtand</hi> the <hi>bleſſings</hi> and gifts of God, wherof it <hi>depriueth</hi> me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. To foreſee the <hi>Euills</hi> into which it <hi>bringeth</hi> me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. And <hi>feare</hi> the <hi>Punishments,</hi> which ſo great an euill <hi>deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Aue Maria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>1.</hi> O Mary Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Yt damned the Angells and caſt them downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. Yt cauſed eternall fyer for their torment. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Yt baniſhed our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts out of Paradiſe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <pb n="204" facs="tcp:151937:114"/>4. Yt depriued them of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; originall iuſtice. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Yt diſordered, &amp; confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded humane nature. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Yt ſubiected the ſame to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, dolours, &amp; death. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Yt put the earth vnder per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall malediction. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Yt filled the world with all kind of miſeries. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. Yt drowned the ſame with the waters of the deluge. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And at the laſt ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it with fire from heauen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>2.</hi> O Mary, Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Yt <hi>taketh from vs</hi> the grace of Baptiſme. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Inheritance of heauen, and euerlaſting bliſſe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. The peace and comfort of a good conſcience. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <pb n="205" facs="tcp:151937:114"/>4. The priuiledges of the iuſt. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. The ſpirituall Ioyes of the deuout. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. The rewardes of good workes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. The harmony, and concord of vertues. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. The gifts of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. The inward beauty &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſoule. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. The meanes and helpes for ſaluation: yea and God him ſelfe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>3.</hi> O Mary, Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter,</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Yt <hi>cauſeth</hi> the hatred of God Almighty. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. A deſire in man that he were not, nor could puniſh him. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. The neglect of his holy wil
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:151937:115"/> and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundments. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. The abhorring of his wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſailes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Ingratitude for his mercyes and benefits. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Rebellion againſt his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Treaſon againſt his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Contempt and Mockery of his ſeruice. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. Infinite oppoſition to his infinite goodnes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally blindnes of hart, and bondage to Sathan &amp; hell. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>4.</hi> O Mary Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Yt <hi>bringeth</hi> ſorrow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of conſcience. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. Feare and horror of death. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Infection from bad to worſe.
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:151937:115"/> 
                           <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. A ſore without ſalue. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Miſery without mercy, or refuge. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Subiection to all curſes and misfortunes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Yt renounceth God by works. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Yt preſumeth (againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) of his mercy. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. Yt aduentureth fooliſhly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his iuſtice. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. Yt exchangeth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good, for the greateſt euill. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>5.</hi> O Mary Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Yt looſeth the Suffrages of holy Church. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. The participation of the meryts of Chriſt. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Yt treadeth vnder foote his
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:151937:116"/> precious bloud. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. Yt reneweth his ſacred wounds and paſſion. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Yt crucifieth him againe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Yt preferreth the ſayings of the world, before the Iudgments of heauen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Yt leaueth Truth for Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Yt changeth wiſdome for Folly. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. It ſelleth the eternall for the momentary. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. It looſeth heauen and gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hell. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>6.</hi> O Mary, Mother of Mercy &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. He that perſeuereth in one ſyn, <hi>deſerueth</hi> that God ſhould permit him to fall into others. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. He deſerueth alſo loſſe of
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:151937:116"/> honor and goods. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Of health, &amp; life. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. And of all other temporall proſperity. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. To haue his memory chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into forgetfulneſſe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. His deſire, and affections depraued &amp; peruerted. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. His vnderſtanding darkned not able to diſcerne his good, nor to beware of his euill. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. That counſaile and ſuccour fayle him in his greateſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. That he be not heard, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelfe, nor by his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates, in life, nor in death. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. That his perſon, and all his affayres be abhorred of God for euer. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>7.</hi> O Mary, Mother of Mercy &amp;c.
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:151937:117"/> Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Obtaine, that I may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>bleſſings,</hi> and great gifts of God whereof it <hi>depriueth</hi> me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. And foreſee the <hi>miſeries</hi> without number, into which it <hi>bringeth</hi> me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. And <hi>feare</hi> the dreadfull <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments</hi> which ſo great an euill <hi>deſerueth. Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer to Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
                     <p>O Eternall Maieſty author &amp; fountayne of all purity, which ſo loueſt it in ſoules made to thy in owne Image, that to clenſe them from ſyn, thou haſt waſhed them with thy precious bloud, neuer ſuffer me to looſe the beauty of thy grace: And graunt to all ſynners that haue loſt the
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:151937:117"/> ſame, true ſorrow &amp; repentance. Amen. <hi>Credo in Deum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayers">
                     <head>A Coronary, or Crowne, with the principall Myſteries of the life, &amp; death of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer to the B. Trinity.</head>
                        <p>O Diuine, and indiuiduall Trinity, who haſt manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted thy Iuſtice, and Mercy, and withall thy infinite Power, wiſdome, and Goodnes, in the Redemption of mankynd, more then in all the other works which thou haſt done: teach me the Soueraigne myſteryes &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the life and Paſſion of my Redeemer; that I may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily reuerence them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:151937:118"/> to imitate them for thy loue. Amen.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To the Omnipotency of the Father. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. To the infinite wiſdome of the Sonne. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. And to the incomprehenſible goodnes of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A prayer in honor of the Mother of God, proper to the firſt Decade.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. O Eternal Prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce who didſt work this ſo great and incomprehenſible a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by giuing to the Diuyne word a Mother of the Children of Adam; make me worthy to ſerue her with all humility, and purity of hart. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. In honor of her immaculate Conception. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <pb n="213" facs="tcp:151937:118"/>2. To her birth ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of mankind. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. To her Preſentation in the Temple. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. How ſhe cooperating care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with the diuyne inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, increaſeth continually in vertue and grace. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. By conſenting with faith &amp; humility to the embaſſage from heauen, God is incarnate, and ſhe becommeth mother <hi>remayning a Virgin. Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. She goeth with diligence vp to the mountaynes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate with S. Elizabeth her coſen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. And with her preſence and voyce S. <hi>Iohn</hi> exulteth, &amp; his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receyueth the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. The Virgin Queene in the houſe of Zachary imployeth her
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:151937:119"/> ſelfe in workes of Charity and humility. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. S. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> wondereth at that which he ſeeth: and remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth perplexed, vntill the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell reuealeth to him the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Aue Maria</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. Such a new and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable worke required appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation from heauen, and an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel for witnes, although the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience be manifeſt, that God becomming man ſhould be born of a Virgin mother. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A prayer to the infancy of Chriſt.</head>
                        <p n="2">2. O Prince of all Eternity, thy Fathers beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, whom Legions of Angells do ſerue in heauen, ſeeing thou vouchſafeſt to come downe to earth; reaſon it is, that all thy
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:151937:119"/> Creatures ſhould go forth to meet thee and ſerue thee: admit me, o Lord for one of the meaneſt ſeruants of thy family. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. He that of nothing made, and vpholdeth all that is created, is borne poore and naked in a ſtable at Bethleem. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. His Angells ſing to him, glory, and peace vpon earth, to men of good conſcience. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. The eighth day he ſheadeth his bloud; and taketh the ſhape of a ſynner. And his Father ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth him with the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which ſignifieth a Sauiour. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. Heauen proclaymeth him King. Herod is troubled. And heathen Princes guided by a ſtar, come from far contries to do him
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:151937:120"/> homage. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. His Parents offer him in the Temple. And where <hi>Symeon</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> foretel his conflicts and victoryes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. With the cruell and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table death of the Innocents, his byrth is publiſhed to all nations. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Aegypt receaueth &amp; imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the King of heauen &amp; earth, whome Iury perſecuteth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. The Angell ſignifieth the death of his Perſecutors. And the Child returneth to Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. He diſcouereth his Diuine wiſdome to the Doctors in the Temple, and ſubiecteth himſelfe with al obedience to his parents. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. He liueth retired eighteene
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:151937:120"/> yeares in <hi>Nazareth;</hi> to teach vs to liue vnknown when it is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; &amp; to expect due ſeaſon for all our workes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer to Christ, as the Guide &amp; Example of our life.</head>
                        <p n="3">3. O Soueraigne Doctor, ſyth the tyme is come wherin thou art pleaſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer thy Eternall ſecretes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men: Make me a worthy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of thy heauenly doctryne. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. The tyme being come for him to performe his office, he leaueth the comfort of his Mother, his houſe, &amp; quietnes, to ſerue the common good. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. He paſſeth alone to the riuer Iordan: where <hi>S. Iohn</hi> Baptiſt diſcouereth him. And they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:151937:121"/> in acts of humility. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. The heauens open themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and the holy Ghoſt deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in a viſible forme. And the Eternall Father ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth him for this Sonne. And commaundeth vs to heare him. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. The great Maiſter of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance retyreth himſelfe to the deſert, to teach vs the ſame by his example, and to be beginne our works with prayer. And there he ouercommeth the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. After he had vanquiſhed the infernal enemy that tempted him, the Angells come to adore, and ſerue him. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. He entertayneth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Saynt <hi>Iohn.</hi> And with his curteſy &amp; ſweetnes obligeth them to his ſeruice. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">
                           <pb n="219" facs="tcp:151937:121"/>7. He ſheweth compaſſion v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſynners. And fatherly care of his ſubiects. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. His patience in all corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wants, and incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. His meeknes in the wrongs and calumniations of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. His miraculous works for the benefit of man, returning al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies good for euil. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A prayer to Christ, in the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of his Paſſion.</head>
                        <p n="4">4. O Louing Maiſter, moſt faythful &amp; only friend, ſeeing thou giueſt me leaue to call thee by this Name: giue me alſo leaue and courage to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company thee as a friend, with loyalty, and loue, in all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſages
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:151937:122"/> of thy Paſſion. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. Hauing fyniſhed the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and ceremonyes of the old Law, with the Paſchall Lambe, he waſheth the feete of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and of <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traytor. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. He leaueth vs for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryall, and pledge of his infinite loue, the new and admirable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his pretious body &amp; bloud. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. He ouercometh all humane infirmities with the force of prayer. And perſeuereth in the ſame ſweating bloud. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. He ſheweth his omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency before he permitteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be taken, that his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies might ſee it was his will to ſuffer. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. That night the Iewes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him vnworthily and cruelly
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:151937:122"/> in the place of Iudgment: and for reaſon of State, conſpired his death, as they thought to ſaue their Commonwealth; which they came to looſe for this very ſame ſyn. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. In the morning they accuſe him before the heathen Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, who admiring his magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity &amp; patience, laboureth to ſet him free. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. He is deſpiſed of <hi>Herod,</hi> and by him attyred with contempt, bycauſe he anſwereth not to his curioſityes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. They teare his ſacred body with moſt cruell ſtripes. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryde the King of glory, with a Crowne of Thornes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. His vnbeleeuing and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull people rebell againſt him, &amp; demaund that he ſhould be crucified. And a malefactour
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:151937:123"/> ſet at liberty in his place. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. The ambitious Iudge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with feare, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, condemneth him to be crucified, though he know him to be innocent. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer to Chriſt, in the ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his death.</head>
                        <p n="5">5. O Author of life, ſyth thou wilt dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and my ſynnes are cauſe of thy death; let me dye with thee, or graunt me a liuely feeling of thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. He imbraceth his deſyred Croſſe with ioy and cheerfulnes of hart: and carrieth it vpon his ſhoulderrs to the place of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. His body beeing weakned with the loſſe of much bloud, he fainteth vnder the grieuous bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:151937:123"/> And the torturers eaſe him leaſt he ſhould dye vncrucified. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. He forbiddeth the deuout women to weepe for him, but for their owne ſynnes and their childrens. And foretelleth the ruyne of that miſerable perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Citty. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. Vpon the Mount Caluary they ſtripping him of his clothes renew his wounds. And he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſacred hands and feete to to be nayled to the Croſſe. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. They lift vp his virginall body naked and nayled. And he ſuffereth this temporall paine &amp; confuſion to deliuer vs from the eternall. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. From the Croſſe he asketh pardon of his Father, for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. He recommendeth his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:151937:124"/> diſciple, &amp; in him al vs to his mother. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. He promiſeth pardon and glory to the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Thiefe. And taſteth gall, and vinagre. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. The propheſies and figures of his paſſion being fulfilled; he giueth vp his moſt holy &amp; pure Spirit into the hands of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth are aſtoniſhed that God immortall ſhould dye. But dying, he killeth ſinne and death, looſeth the chaines of Hel, reconcileth the world to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reſtoreth man to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A prayer to Chriſt, reuiued and triumphant.</head>
                        <p n="6">6. O Glorious Conqueror who art riſen from death enriched with ſpoyles, &amp;
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:151937:124"/> haſt al power in heauen &amp; earth: Let ſynne dye in me, without which there is no death. And giue me a new life, which may pleaſe thee &amp; ſerue thee for euer. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. He ſheweth himſelfe aliue, and glorious vnto his Bleſſed Mother &amp; diſciples. And chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth their ſorrow into vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable ioy. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. After forty dayes he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with triumph into heauen to take poſſeſſion of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; placed our humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on the right hand of God his Father. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. His diſciples in company of his holy mother retyred in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, expect from heauen the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter promiſed. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. The time being fullfilled, the holy Ghoſt deſcendeth viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:151937:125"/> vpon them in forme of fiery tongues. And they publiſh the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne Chriſtian miſteryes of faith in diuers languages. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. The playne, &amp; vnpoliſhed words of the Apoſtles receauing force from this Spirit, take po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſion in the harts of men. And thouſands are conuerted togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. By the death and prayers of of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> Paul of a perſecutor becometh an Apoſtle. The fayth increaſeth with the perſecution, and with the ſame ſpread into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countreys. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. The Apoſtles meete in Councell, ordeyne the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and deuide among themſelues the Prouinces of the whole world; which is conuerted, as we ſee, to Chriſt by twelue Fiſhermen: ſo great is
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:151937:125"/> the force of this holy Spirit. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> remayneth in Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem with the Mother of God for her comfort. And their admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life and example authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth the fayth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. The Apoſtles miraculou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly come togeather at the death of the B. Virgin. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And her Soule departeth without payne, out of the priſon of her body. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>A Prayer in the exequies of our B. Lady, with the Apoſtles.</head>
                        <p n="7">7. O Lord, what happines had it byn to be with thy diſciples at thoſe Funeralls, &amp; to haue celebrated thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull greatnes and prayſes, for the benefits receyued, by this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:151937:126"/> Virgin. <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. Her ſoule the third day was reunited to her glorious body. And aſſumpted into heauen with ſuch ſolemnity, as no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man can comprehend. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. The moſt humble of all creatures, is exalted aboue them all. And crowned Queene of heauen and earth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Amongſt other prerogatiues, which the Bleſſed Virgin enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and wherin eſpecially ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth, is to be the Aduocate of ſinners with Chriſt our Sauiour. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <head>The Concluſion with thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</head>
                        <p>LET Heauen and earth ioyne together with ioy, and the Quiers of Angells with the voices of men, to ſinge eternall
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:151937:126"/> prayſes vnto God in Trinity and vnity, for the mercyes receaued in this admirable work of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amen. <hi>Credo in Deum &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Coronary, or Crowne, for the obtayning of Christian Perfection.</head>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O My Lord Ieſu Chriſt, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of the Father, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wiſdome; graunt me true knowledge, continuall memory and a cordiall deſire of the moſt noble, and moſt precious end, wherunto thou haſt created me; and a right choyce of the meanes which thou gaſt giuen me to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. Amen.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. My principall end for which I was created, is to loue, obay and pleaſe Almighty God.
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:151937:127"/> And the ſecondary or leſſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall is to ſaue my ſoule. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. The <hi>meanes</hi> for this end are all other creatures, &amp; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; good vſe of them. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. This <hi>vſe</hi> conſiſteth in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or diminiſhing, taking or leauing them, by waight, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; meaſure as they may ſerue this end. The diſpoſition nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary to vſe them aright is to be indifferent to all. And in the <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> that we preferre allwaies the more conuenient for this end, before the leſſe, and the better before the worſe. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>1.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Make me vnderſtand (o Lord) that for thy only goodnes thou louedſt me from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And hauing no need of me, thou haſt created me to thy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:151937:127"/> &amp; likenes in the tyme moſt conuenient for my good. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. And how thou haſt placed me as a King in his Kingdome, with iuſtice, peace, and inward ioy of my ſoule. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. That thou haſt made me a companion of the Angells, and capable of all thy riches, and (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all) of thy grace and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. That I knowing thy infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodnes by experience, and thy ſelfe by familiar conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might delight in thee, and loue thee aboue all things with pure and diſintereſſed loue. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. That I may ſerue thee for thy ſelfe, with all the powers of my body and ſoule, bycauſe thou deſerueſt to be ſerued and loued aboue all. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <pb n="232" facs="tcp:151937:128"/>6 That in all things, I may procure thy greater glory, and the perfect accompliſhment of thy diuine will. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. That I may deſire and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure by all the wayes I can, that thou be knowne, loued, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified of all men. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. That I may reioyce for the good of others, and by charity haue part in their happines. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. And afterwards receaue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in thy Kingdome, for that which by thy grace I ſhall haue deſerued. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of thy glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a perfect Image and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayture of thy Diuine Nature for euer. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>2.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="233" facs="tcp:151937:128"/>1. O Lord, let me loue this ſo amiable and ſoueraigne good, which thou haſt prouided for me aboue all gold, ſiluer, and precious ſtones. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. And aboue all other trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and ryches of the earth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Aboue all liberty and eaſe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. Aboue all other delights and pleaſures. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Aboue all power &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Aboue all honor &amp; popular applauſe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. And aboue al authority and dominion. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Aboue all loue, kindred, and other perſons, moſt loued and eſteemed. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. Aboue all health, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">
                           <pb n="234" facs="tcp:151937:129"/>10. And finally aboue all that is not God. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>3.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r Noſter.</head>
                        <p>O Lord let me vnderſtand the breadth, length, height, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundity of thy infinite charity wherewith thou haſt geuen me,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Thy holy Spirit for my Comforter. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. Thy Angells for my Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and protectors, <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. Thy Law for my inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. Thy Sayntes for my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Thy Sacraments for the health of my ſoule. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. A Bath of thy moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud wherin to waſh me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Thy Bleſſed body in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the altar wherwith
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:151937:129"/> to nouriſh me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Thy puniſhments for my warning, and thy comforts to giue me courage. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. All thy creatures for my ſeruice. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally reaſon, fayth, thy diuine prouidence &amp; father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protection, for guides of my way in this pilgrimage wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I liue, that through thy mercy I may obtayne this ſo high and ſoueraigne an end, for which thou haſt made me. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>4.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p>Teach me (o Lord) the good vſe of theſe good meanes, which with ſo bountifull a hand thou haſt giuen me: And of thy good creatures which thou haſt made ſubiect to my liberty, that they may not hinder, but help me to
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:151937:130"/> this end.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Giue me knowledge how to keep warily my exteriour ſenſes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. To vſe my Memory with diſcretion. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. My Iudgment with truth &amp; reaſon. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. My Intention with recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. My Will with purity. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Thy Sacraments with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Proſperity with thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Aduerſity with patience. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. Things indifferent with all indifferency of mind. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally, to behold this world as a booke ful of certain &amp; manifeſt teſtimonyes of thy Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gments, and mercies, and of thy
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:151937:130"/> infinite wiſdome, omnipotency and admirable loue. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>5.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Graunt vnto me ſhame and confuſion for my faults and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligences paſt, as offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thy diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. And a firme Purpoſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them, and to ſatisfy for them as I ſhalbe able. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. And Prouidence to auoid occaſions, not to fall into the like hereafter. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. And Fortitude wherwith to ouercome all temptations and hinderaunces of thy ſeruice. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. Care, and account how I ſpend the tyme which paſſeth, and cannot be recalled. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. And ſorrow for that which
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:151937:131"/> I haue loſt, forgetting thee and my ſelfe. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. Feare to looſe thy grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all loſſes. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Compaſſion of thoſe which haue loſt it, without care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer it. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. And zeale of ſoules bought with thy pretious bloud. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally a cordiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, that all may be ſaued, ſith thou ſo deſireſt it, and didſt dye for all. And a principall care that none come into daunger, and much leſſe periſh through my fault. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>6.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Chriſt &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p>Graunt me (o Lord) light from heauen, and wiſdome to procure in all my workes the beſt &amp; moſt pleaſing to thy Diuine Maieſty,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. To chuſe always that which
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:151937:131"/> is certaine before the doubtfull. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. That which is truely good, before that which is fayned. <hi>Aue.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. To preferre the Principall, before the Acceſſory, and leſſe worthy. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. And that which laſteth for euer, before that which peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. To eſteeme the vniuerſal good before my particuler. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. Health before delight. <hi>Aue.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="7">7. That which is iuſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, before that which is only profitable. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. Vertue before vice. <hi>Aue Ma.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. The Soule before the body. <hi>A.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. And finally Heauen (which muſt be our Eternall manſion) before the earth, which only ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for a paſſage and tryall. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe (as a better &amp; greater
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:151937:132"/> good) participate more of thy goodnes, and are more confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to thy good pleaſure and holy will; which be euer fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, obeyed, and reuerenced, in Heauen, and in Earth. Amen. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="part">
                        <head>
                           <hi>7.</hi> O my Lord Ieſu Christ &amp;c. Pater Noſter.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Graunt me (o Lord) true <hi>knowledge,</hi> &amp; continuall memory of my <hi>principall end,</hi> which is to loue, obey, &amp; pleaſe thee. <hi>Aue M.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. Alſo true <hi>knowledge</hi> &amp; <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual memory</hi> of the <hi>ſecondary</hi> &amp; leſſe principall; which is to ſaue my Soule. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. And a <hi>right vſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>choyce</hi> of the meanes which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me, wherby to obtayne E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happines. <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Credo in Deum.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="instructions">
                     <pb n="241" facs="tcp:151937:132"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ADVERTISMENTS FOR THOSE</hi> who will ſay with greater deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpirituall comfort the foreſaid Coronaryes.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. ALL Acts of Vertue, with cuſtome are made delightefull: and ſuch as make triall, come to knowe that it is much more eaſy to ſerue God then the Diuell; and more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; confortable to ſerue God with feruour, then with negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and without all compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be a Saint, then a ſynner.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For in ſeruing of God, the
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:151937:133"/> pleaſures are not only pure without diſtaſt, but much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more durable then thoſe which the world can affoard to her Louers. Beſides the ſpirituall powers are more actiue and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as the obiects are more noble, and fit to cauſe greater comforts; and therfore conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from both theſe grounds the acts are much more perfect; &amp; ſo full of delight that they are able to ſweeten the greateſt byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes. As we ſee by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his greateſt tribulations, by the Martyrs in their torments, &amp; by other Saints and ſeruants of God in all the aduerſities of this life.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Creatures vſed with the moderation which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, and with that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect which is due vnto him, are profitable vnto vs, and do bring
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:151937:133"/> with them lawfull contentment &amp; pleaſure. Otherwiſe they are chaunged into torment &amp; gall. This good, profitable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vſe of Gods Creatures wilbe much holpen and ſteng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by the practiſe of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronaries which diſcouer their v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilities and domages: obſeruing well by way of prayer, the truths which are adioyned vnto them, and waighing the force of euery one of them in particuler, and the conſequence and connexion which they haue one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to informe therby and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuate the vnderſtanding, and diſpoſe the will to that which is conuenient. For in prayer, when the ſoule is more retired from corporall obiects, and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to God; many thinges are cleerly ſeene, which otherwiſe,
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:151937:134"/> for want of light, may eaſily be miſtaken: and we are better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, to heare what his diuine maieſty ſpeaketh inwardly to vs as the Prophet ſayd, <hi>Audiam quid loquatur in me Dominus, qui loquitur pacem in plebem ſuam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. All Creatures, repreſented to the ſight, as they haue their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; ſo haue they their tongues and language. And all the truths which we heare, or read in bookes, and the good or euill ſucceſſes which happen to our ſelues or to others, are ſo many words which God Almighty ſpeaketh vnto vs by his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And may all be occaſion and matter of prayer.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For <hi>Prayer</hi> is nothing elſe but a ſweet conuerſation with God, author of all good gifts: like vnto that which we haue
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:151937:134"/> with any other perſon beloued, and of reſpect; to giue him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt of all that concerneth vs, and to aſke his counſayle in our doubts, and help in our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; or to giue him thanks for the benefits which he beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vpon vs.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And notwithſtanding God Almighty knoweth all that we can tell him, and is much more ready to do vs good then we are to aske it; yet it is his ordinary Law, and a thing due to the greatnes of his gifts, that we muſt aske them to obtayn them, and being obtayned it is duty and iuſtice to giue him thanks. Moreouer (as a louing Father) he delighteth that we haue often recourſe vnto him, and giue him particuler account of what we do and pretend. And that we
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:151937:135"/> deſire and reioice to liue always in his preſence.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. So that (without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) he which knoweth to chang the perſon, and conuerſe with God after the ſame manner we conuerſe with men (obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing allwaies the reuerence due to ſo great a Maieſty) ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted with contynuall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable prayer, and feele ſpeedily the fruit therof in his ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. And becauſe this may be done foure ſeuerall wayes; there be alſo ſo many wayes of prayer to wit <hi>Naturall, Doctrinall, Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mixt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>Naturall Prayer,</hi> is ſo called for the naturall manner wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is effected: hearing and pondering with attention that which God ſpeaketh vnto vs in his creatures, or in any good
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:151937:135"/> booke which we read, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as hath byn ſaid. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pawſed a litle and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therof, let that which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth be giuen for anſwere playnly and deuoutly vnto God, as if he were viſibly preſent, or any other perſon ſpeaking with vs, to whome we ſhould giue anſwere.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. <hi>Doctrinall Prayer,</hi> imployeth al the powers of the ſoule &amp; body and their acts: <hi>Memory</hi> obſeruing; the <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> pondering; the <hi>VVill</hi> feeling ſpiritually: the <hi>Senſes</hi> working; &amp; the toung ſpeaking to God of that matter which is propoſed.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. And conformable to theſe acts, may be made ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds vpon euery one of the poynts of theſe Coronaries: or vpon any other matter of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:151937:136"/> or prayer.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. As for example, I will meditate vpon the firſt words of the third Coronary, <hi>That God thought of me, and loued me from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</hi> Hauing recollected my ſelfe in his preſence, and formed an imaginary place to help me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſtraction, with other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary preparations, I demaund firſt of my ſelfe: <hi>VVhat is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued</hi> in the words aboue ſaid; &amp; I anſwere: <hi>An infinite happynes:</hi> as if I had found a great treaſure, not knowing how much it is. And to ground my ſelfe in this truth, with a deſyre to vnderſtand it better, goe forward to examine it in the point following.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Secondly I demaund, <hi>what is to be weighed &amp; conſidered</hi> in the ſame? And I fynd, An infinite worthynes, and obligation to
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:151937:136"/> eſteeme my ſoule as God eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it; and to correſpond to his loue with perpetuall thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to keepe it with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary care, ſeeing he loued it from all eternity. And for my better inſtruction I will take for counterpoize in this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the like particular loue of a Prince (if it were poſſible) to his ſeruaunt; and how much the gratefull and diſcreet ſeruant would eſteeme therof, and how thankefull he would be for it to his Lord. And comparing it with this wherof we treate, I ſhall find an infinite difference. And in this place are to be weighed alſo the cauſes, effects, and circumſtances of that which we meditate, and would compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Thirdly I demaund, <hi>what
<pb n="350" facs="tcp:151937:137"/> muſt I feele in conſequence of that which</hi> I haue obſerued, and waighed. I anſwere; A profound humility, an enflamed loue, inward griefe, and repentance, thankefulnes, prayſe, ioy, and circumſpection, bycauſe there is ground for all theſe affects, and other ſuch like: confirming &amp; delighting my ſelf in them, with the power of my free will.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Fourthly I demaund, <hi>what am I to doe,</hi> according to all this? And I anſwere: I will treate how to execute fruitfully the good purpoſes which our Lord inſpireth me, and apply effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meanes in particular, to the end, that what I haue purpoſed may be fulfilled in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and in the beſt tyme poſſible &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Fiftly I demaund, <hi>what am
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:151937:137"/> I to ſay to our Lord concerning this point:</hi> And I anſwere; I will offer vnto him all my good purpoſes and deſyres to be confirmed by him: and treate with him of the meanes conſidered, deſiring him to direct me in them. I will alſo repreſent vnto him, my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes with ſhame and ſorrow, that I haue purpoſed many other tymes the like, which I haue not performed. And finally exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the patience and mercy wherwith he hath ſuffered my negligence &amp; inconſtancy, I wil aske him forgiuenes from the bottome of my hart, and what more he ſhall inſpire into me. And this may ſuffice for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond manner of prayer.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. The third which is <hi>Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> is not ſubiect to rule; bycauſe it hath the Holy Ghoſt for mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.
<pb n="352" facs="tcp:151937:138"/> And comonly it is graunted to ſuch as are very humble and deuoute; and haue exerciſed themſelues long tyme in theſe or like formes of praying; or it is giuen in reward of ſome great tribulation, ſuffered for God with patience, or of ſome other notable and heroicall worke: And then is ſecure of illuſion, when it moueth to do good works; &amp; ſpecially without feare when it is acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with true humility, for theſe be ſignes of the ſpirit of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. The fourth kind of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is Mixt, which in part is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to rule, and in part is not. In the ſecond manner of prayer ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, the order in the acts &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands there me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be obſerued. For ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> giueth ſo great light &amp;
<pb n="353" facs="tcp:151937:138"/> cleernes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very beginning; &amp; moueth the hart of him that prayeth in ſuch manner, that the prayer is begon and ended with a familiar ſpeach with his diuine Maieſty, or with ſome affect of admiration, of thanksgiuing, of loue, of compaſſion, or the like.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. But aboue all it is to be vnderſtood and obſerued, that Prayer is a peculier gift of God: as likewiſe are all the acts and affections of it aboue ſaid. For many do ſee, heare, and read much, and yet obſerue not any thing to this purpoſe. Others do obſerue ſuperficially, but do not weigh nor ponder deeply to this end that which they haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Some alſo know to ponder, yea &amp; how to moue others with their wordes: and yet haue little feeling themſelues of that which
<pb n="354" facs="tcp:151937:139"/> they ſay, becauſe it is a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gift of God to haue feeling &amp; deuotion in ſuch ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffayres. Others haue feeling but worke not accordingly, bycauſe they ſuffer themſelues to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with the difficultyes which our depraued nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth, and the Diuell ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth and nouriſheth; to the end that the good purpoſes made be not put in execution. But to conclude: <hi>who liueth wel, prayeth wel.</hi> And although he be briefe and barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in words, yet wil our Lord that looketh into his intention and workes heare him willingly and diſpatch him with great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, if he be found loyal and gratefull for benefits receyued. And ſo much more abundantly, by how much he is more free &amp; liberall with his diuine Maieſty.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <pb n="355" facs="tcp:151937:139"/>20. <hi>Prayer is the Golden Key,</hi> which openeth the gates of Royall Pallaces, euen to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermoſt cloſets: And at all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers giueth free entrance, and acceſſe to the King.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. And if the naturall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which men fynd in liuing neare vnto thoſe, who in ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power reſemble God, (&amp; ſo much the more by how much they are more like vnto him in iuſtice and goodnes) be ſufficient to ouercome all the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modityes and labours, which thoſe that ſerue Kings &amp; Princes do endure continually in their ſeruice: What pleaſure is it to ſerue neere vnto God himſelfe, &amp; to be conuerſant with him, and to haue free entrance to his preſence, at all houres, and in al places, by meanes of <hi>Prayer?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="22">
                        <pb n="356" facs="tcp:151937:140"/>22. His conuerſation is ſo ſweet and his preſence ſo delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that the bleſſed Spirits doe, and ſhall entertayne themſelues therewith for all eternity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wearynes, or deſyre to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy any other good.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Yea, we ſee heere vpon earth that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>S. Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> and many ſuch others that gaue themſelues wholy to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and contemplatiue life, liued many yeares in the wildernes &amp; muſt ſolitary deſerts, with great ioy and contentment, fynding no want of conuerſation with men, nor of the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and pleaſures of Cittyes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficiently e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tertayned with this only comunication and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation with God, by meanes of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="24">24. And ſo we read of Saint
<pb n="357" facs="tcp:151937:140"/> 
                        <hi>Anthony,</hi> that after he had ſpent all the night in prayer, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned of the Sunne which he had left behind his backe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, &amp; when in the morning it did ariſe in his face, troubled his attention, and the quietnes of his prayer.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. <hi>Prayer</hi> made the ſame <hi>S. Anthony</hi> ſo learned without vſe of bookes, that he aſtoniſhed the Philoſophers of Alexandria that came to ſee him: becauſe he had his light from heauen; and the whole vniuerſity of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſerued him for a library. And whoſoeuer ſtudieth as he ſhould in this library of S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> cannot faile to proue both wiſe and learned.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. <hi>Prayer</hi> guided King <hi>Dauid</hi> in the gouernment of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; and is an excellent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour
<pb n="358" facs="tcp:151937:141"/> of Kings, and of all thoſe that do manage waighty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffayres; not to erre in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Ioſue</hi> erred when he was deceyued by the <hi>Gabionites;</hi> bycauſe he did not conſult his reſolution with God nor aske him counſaile in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before he gaue them anſwere.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. And (to conclude in one word the profit and dignity of <hi>Prayer</hi>) it maketh men like vnto Angells, who (without loſing the ſight of their God) worke &amp; accompliſh his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundments and they alwayes worke aright, and are not ſubiect to error, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they worke alwayes with the knowledge which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue from the fountaine of light.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. It is an Angelicall life, to liue and worke in the preſence of God: as it is of bruite beaſts,
<pb n="359" facs="tcp:151937:141"/> to ſpend the time in forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of him &amp; without the vſe of prayer. The felicity of beaſts is to ſeeke only delight in ſenſuall pleaſures, without thanks for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitts receyued, or memory of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s preſent, or prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of neceſſities to come. But man by the dignity of his nature, is bound to more: becauſe his ſoule is immortall, and his body ſhall riſe again from death, and both together enioy for euer that which they haue prouided toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for themſelues in this life, with God in eternall felicity, or with the damned ſpirits in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and torments that neuer ſhall haue end, from which God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs for his mercy. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:151937:142"/>
                     <pb n="261" facs="tcp:151937:142"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>A PRAYER</hi> to our Bleſſed Lady.</head>
                     <p>O Moſt pious Virgin Mary, Mother of God: in moſt humble manner I beſeech thee, by the great loue, thou beareſt to thy deare Sonne, my Lord and Sauiour Ieſus-Chriſt: That thou wouldeſt vouchſafe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne for me true ſorrow for my ſinnes, a perfect keeping of all my Senſes, an humble Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſelfe, &amp; the exerciſe of thoſe vertues wherewith thou didſt ſo highly pleaſe thy diuine Sonne. I alſo moſt humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thee to direct my wayes in thoſe pathes which may be moſt agreable to the wil of thy Sonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and profitable for the ſaluation of my Soule. Amen, ſweet Ieſus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="262" facs="tcp:151937:143" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>AN ACT OF CONTRITION.</head>
                     <p>O My Lord Ieſus Chriſt true God and Man, my Creatour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, thou being whome thou art, and for that I loue thee aboue all thinges, it grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me from the bottome of my hart, that I haue offended thy diuin Maieſty. Loe heere I firmely purpoſe neuer to ſinne any more; and to fly all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of offending thee: And to confeſſe and fulfill the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ance which ſhalbe enioyned me for the ſame. And for loue of thee, I do freely pardon all
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151937:143"/> my enemies. And do offer my life, wordes, and workes in ſatisfaction for my ſinnes. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="7 letters">
                           <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                        </gap> I moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, truſting in thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goones and mercy, that by the merites of thy moſt pretious bloud and paſſion, thou wouldeſt pardon me, &amp; giue me grace to amend my life, and to perſeuere therin vntill death. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
